<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Memorials of worthy persons two decads / by Cl. Barksdale.</title>
            <title>Memorials of worthy persons. Decades 1-2</title>
            <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1661</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 154 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 108 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A30949</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B800</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8737</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11983348</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11983348</idno>
            <idno type="VID">51903</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A30949)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 51903)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 52:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Memorials of worthy persons two decads / by Cl. Barksdale.</title>
                  <title>Memorials of worthy persons. Decades 1-2</title>
                  <author>Barksdale, Clement, 1609-1687.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[10], 204 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by I.R.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1661.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reissued as: Characters and historical memorials, on the lives and actions of England's late worthies. 1662.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Biography.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Stuarts, 1603-1714 --  Biography.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:1"/>
            <p>MEMORIALS OF WORTHY PERSONS: Two <hi>Decads.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By CL. BARKSDALE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Memory of the Just is bleſsed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>I. R.</hi> 1661.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:2"/>
            <head>The Names of the Perſons.</head>
            <list>
               <item>Dr. Joſeph Hall Biſhop of <hi>Norwich.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. John Donne, Dean of <hi>S. Paul's.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir. Will. Cokain <hi>Ald.</hi> of <hi>London.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Sir Thomas Bodley.</item>
               <item>D. John Jewel <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. George Herbert.</item>
               <item>Dr. James Uſher <hi>A B.</hi> of <hi>Armagh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. John Hales of <hi>Eton.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>R. Evelyn.</item>
               <item>Dr. Art. Lake <hi>B.</hi> of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Edward Peyto <hi>Eſq;</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. Will. Laud <hi>A Biſhop</hi> of <hi>Cant.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Arc-Biſhop Uſher.</item>
               <item>Thomas Brandeſton. of <hi>Barfold.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. John Dod.</item>
               <item>Mr. Joſeph Mede.</item>
               <item>Mr. Joſias Shute.</item>
               <item>Francis Bacon <hi>L. Verulam.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Dr. Thomas Jackson.</item>
               <item>Lady Falkland</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:2"/>
            <head>TO HIS <hi>Honourable Friend,</hi> GEORGE MOUNTAGU Eſq;</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat you have in your Family Three Knights of the <hi>Garter,</hi> is a great honour; but 'tis a great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er honour, that there be in your Family many more, excelling in Cour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſie,
<pb facs="tcp:51903:3"/> and Valour, and Loyalty, and Prudence, and in that which is <hi>the Head of Wiſdome, the Fear God.</hi> Where the fear of God is, there alſo dwel's a <hi>Reverence</hi> to the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of God, the <hi>Fathers</hi> and <hi>Doctours</hi> of the Church: Of which Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity are moſt of the Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons remembred in theſe <hi>papers,</hi> which I have <hi>guild<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> as it were, and beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tified with your flouriſh, ing Name. Some <hi>Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen</hi> are here mixed
<pb facs="tcp:51903:3"/> with the <hi>Church-men.</hi> And I heartily pray, they may be alwaies conjoyned, and lovingly united, for their mutual, both tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral and eternal, happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Theſe <hi>Memorials</hi> are of the <hi>Deceaſed</hi> onely. I believe we have their Equals of both ſorts now <hi>Living.</hi> Whom God in mercy hath reſcued from the late Calamities, and reſerved for Himſelf and for his Vice-gerent our moſt Cracious <hi>Soveraign,</hi> that they might ſerve
<pb facs="tcp:51903:4"/> Him in this bleſſed <hi>Reſtau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> of Church and State. May they happily go on; and You, <hi>Right Noble Sir,</hi> among the firſt Ranks, to deſerve that <hi>Glory,</hi> which, if they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive not at preſent from an Ingrateful Age, Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity will ſurely render to their Memories.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt obliged and moſt affectionate ſervant CL. BARKSDALE.</signed> 
               <dateline>
                  <date>April 23.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:4"/>
            <head>TO THE READER,</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Purpoſe, God willing, to go on in this way of <hi>Collection,</hi> to revive the <hi>Memory</hi> and ſpread the <hi>Fame</hi> of excellent <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Women</hi> of our Church, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving this alſo to be a means to gain the Affections, and recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile thoſe that ſtand at a diſtance from us; when they ſee what <hi>ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly perſons</hi> this Church hath been (and is) adorned with. Know, that the <hi>Authours</hi> at the end, ſhould have been cited at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of every <hi>Memorial</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectively.
<pb facs="tcp:51903:5"/> The most conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>Errata,</hi> be pleaſed, before reading of the book, to correct with the pen, thus:</p>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>Errata.</head>
            <p>22. <hi>ult. Iz. W. 76. 5. often. 87. 14. Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chet. 101. 10. the P. 102. 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oint. 109. 16. Poit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>u 123. 13. adde out of</hi> Dr. Gauden's <hi>Suſpir. 126 5. out of</hi> Mr. Fullers <hi>Church hiſt. 136. 2. Suſpiria. 119. 1. Man<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ree. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>44. 9. fift Command. 178. 3. Common.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:5"/>
            <head>I. Decad.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Dr. Joſeph Hall B. <hi>of Nor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wich.</hi> 1.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>I. Dr. John Donne, Dean of St. <hi>Pauls</hi> 15.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>II. Sir William Cokain Ald. of <hi>Lond.</hi> 23.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>V. Sir Tho. Bodley. 32.</item>
               <item>V. Dr. John Jewell Biſhop of <hi>Sarum.</hi> 44.</item>
               <item>VI. Mr. Geo. Herbert. 62.</item>
               <item>VII. Dr. James Uſher A B. of <hi>Armagh.</hi> 66.</item>
               <item>VIII. Mr. John Hales of <hi>Eton.</hi> 70.</item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>X. R. Evelyn. 76.</item>
               <item>X. Dr. Arthur Lake B. of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi> 86.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:6"/>
            <head>II Decad.</head>
            <list>
               <item>I. Edward Peyto <hi>Eſq;</hi> 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>II. Dr. William <hi>Laud</hi> A B. o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Canterbury.</hi> 116</item>
               <item>III. Arch-B. Usſher. 126</item>
               <item>IV. Tho. Brandeſton of <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold.</hi> 136</item>
               <item>V. Mr John Dod. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>VI. Mr. Joſeph Mede. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>VII. Mr. Joſias Shute. 16<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>VIII. Francis Bacon <hi>L. Veru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lam.</hi> 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>IX. Dr. Tho Jackſon. 18<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
               <item>X. Lady Falkland. 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="biographies">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:51903:6"/>
            <div n="1" type="biography">
               <head>I. Dr. JOSEPH HALL <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Norwich.</head>
               <p>1. <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>E was noted for a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Wit from his youth; a moſt acute <hi>Rhetorician,</hi> and an elegant <hi>Poet.</hi> Two yeares toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he was choſen <hi>Rhetorick</hi>-Profeſſor in the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> and performed the Office with extraordinary ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plauſe.</p>
               <p>2. Whil'ſt he was the pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Paſtor firſt of <hi>Halsted</hi> in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and after at <hi>Waltham</hi> in <hi>Eſſex,</hi> he preached thrice a
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:51903:7"/> week in a conſtant courſe; yet (as himſelf witneſſeth) never durſt clime up into the Pulpit to preach any Sermon, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he had not before penn'd e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very word in the ſame order, wherein he hoped to deliver it: although in his expreſſions he was no ſlave to ſyllables, neither made uſe of his Notes.</p>
               <p>3. It is well known in this City, how forward he was to Preach in any of our Churches, till he was firſt forbidden by men, and at laſt diſenabled by God. And when he could not Preach himſelf; this learned <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maliel</hi> was not content onely, but very diligent to ſit at the feet of the youngeſt of his Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciples; as diligent an Hearer as he had been a Preacher.</p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:51903:7"/>
               <p>3. In his employment to the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> he had great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect there from the Forreign Divines and States. And in thoſe unhappy Diſputes he ſhewed excellent Moderation. Concerning which, he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward drew up ſuch a Collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of accorded Truths, as was offered to be ſubſcribed by ſome of the moſt eminent on both ſides. Which reconciliatory Papers then unhappily buried, are very much deſired, and may be hoped for in time; together with an account of his life, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by himſelf.</p>
               <p>5. What <hi>Nazianzene</hi> ſaid of <hi>Baſil</hi> may be applied to him; <hi>Et eruditis pietate, &amp; pits erudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionis laude antecelluit.</hi> Thoſe that were moſt eminent for
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:51903:8"/> Learning he excelled in Piety, and thoſe that were moſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous for Piety he excelled in Learning.</p>
               <p>6. He was a rare Mirrour of Patience under all his Croſſes, which toward his latter end were multiplied upon him. I have heard him oft bewail the ſpoils of the Church, but very ſeldome did he ſo much as men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion his own loſſes.</p>
               <p>6. Beſides his ſpiritual Almes of Prayers, godly Admonitions, Comforts and holy Counſells, whereof he was very liberal, his bodily Almes were con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant and bountifull: he gave a weekly contribution to poor Widdows, to his dying day; and by his Will, a good ſumme of money to the Town
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:51903:8"/> where he was born, and to this City where he died.</p>
               <p>8. For his Children, I may ſay, as <hi>Ambroſe</hi> of <hi>Theodoſius, Non totus receſsit, &amp;c.</hi> He is not all gone; he hath left us his Sons, in whom we may yet ſee him and enjoy him. For his Works, I may with reverence ſay of them as the <hi>Pſalm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God's, <hi>They all praiſe him,</hi> becauſe all men praiſe them.</p>
               <byline>Out of his Funerall Sermon by <hi>Mr. John Lightfoot, 1656.</hi>
               </byline>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="biography">
               <head>II. Dr. JOHN DONNE <hi>Dean of</hi> St. Paul's.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HE was born in <hi>London,</hi> of good and virtuous Parents: his Father lineally de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended from a very ancient
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:51903:9"/> Family in <hi>Wal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s;</hi> his Mother from the Family of the famous Sr. <hi>Thomas More,</hi> ſomtimes Lord Chancellour of <hi>England.</hi> But his own Learning and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther multipli'd merits may juſtly ſeem ſufficient to dignifie both himſelf and poſterity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Being nine years of age he was ſent to the Univerſity of <hi>Oxofrd;</hi> having at that time a command of the <hi>French</hi> and <hi>Latin</hi> Tongues, when others can ſearce ſpeak their own.</p>
               <p>About the fourteenth year of his age, he was tranſplanted to <hi>Cambridge;</hi> where (that he might receive nouriſhment from both ſoils) he ſtay'd til his ſeaventeenth year. All which time he was a moſt laborious Student, often changing his
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:51903:9"/> Studies. Then was he removed to <hi>London,</hi> and entred into <hi>Lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coln's Inne,</hi> where he gave great teſtimonies of wit, learning, and improvement in the ſtudy of the Law.</p>
               <p n="3">3. About his nineteenth year, being unreſolved in Religion, waving the Law, he began to ſurvey the Body of Divinity, controverted between the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed and <hi>Roman</hi> Church, and in that ſearch &amp; diſquiſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, he proceeded with humility and diffidence in himſelf, by the ſafeſt way of frequent Prayers, and indifferent affection to both Parties. And indeed Truth had too much light a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout her, to be hid from ſo ſharp an enquirer; and he had too much ingenuity, not to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:51903:10"/> he had ſeen h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</p>
               <p n="4">4. About the twentieth year of his age, he travelled, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned not into <hi>England,</hi> till he had ſtay'd a convenient time, firſt in <hi>Italy,</hi> and then in <hi>Spain;</hi> where he made many uſefull obſervations of thoſe Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treys, their Lawes and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and returned into <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> perfect in their languages.</p>
               <p n="5">5. Not long after his return, that exemplary pattern of wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and gravity, the Lord <hi>Elſmore,</hi> Lord keeper of the Great Seal, taking notice of his Learning, Languages and other abilities, and much affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting both his perſon and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, received him to be his chief Secretary, ſuppoſing it might be an Introduction to ſome more weighty employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:51903:10"/> in the State: for which his Lordſhip often proteſted, he thought him very fit; and at his diſmiſſion ſaid, he was a Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary fitter for a King then a Subject.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Afterward, he lived many yeares with his noble Kinſman Sr. <hi>Francis Wally</hi> of <hi>Pirford,</hi> where he ſtudied the Civil and Canon Laws: in which he acquired ſuch a perfection, as was judged to hold ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion with many, who had made that ſtudy the employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their whole life.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Sr. <hi>Francis</hi> being dead, he was importuned and perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by his friends, to make his reſidence in <hi>London:</hi> where that Honourable Gentleman Sr. <hi>Robert Drury</hi> aſſigned him
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:51903:11"/> a very convenient Houſe Rent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>free, next his own in <hi>Drury-Lane;</hi> and was alſo a dayly che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſher of his ſtudies.</p>
               <p n="8">8. His Majeſty had formerly both known and much valued him, and had given him ſome hopes of a State-employment, being much pleaſed, that Mr. <hi>Donne</hi> attended him, eſpecially at his meales; where there was uſually many deep diſcourſes of Learning, and diſputes of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: and particularly at that time, concerning the Oath of Supremacy and Allegiance; which was the occaſion of Mr. <hi>Donne</hi>'s writing his <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſeudomar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. When the King had read and conſidered that Book, he perſwaded Mr. <hi>Donne</hi> to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:51903:11"/> into the Miniſtry: &amp; though many friends mediated with his Majeſty to prefer him to ſome Civil employment, to which his Education had apted him; yet the King denyed their requeſts, and having a diſcern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſpirit, replyed: <hi>I know</hi> Mr. Donne <hi>is a Learned man, an excellent Divine, and will prove a powerfull Preacher.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Yet he deferred to enter into ſacred Orders for the ſpace of three yeares: all which time he applied himſelf to an inceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant ſtudy of Textuall Divinity, and attained a greater perrfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the Learned Languages, Greek and Hebrew. And then declaring his intention to his dear friend Dr. <hi>King,</hi> the then worthy Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:51903:12"/> Reverend Biſhop moſt gladly received the newes, and with all convenient ſpeed ordained him Deacon and Prieſt.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Now all his ſtudies (which were occaſionally dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fus'd) were concentred in Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity: Now he had a new cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, new thoughts, new em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment for his wit and elo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence. Now all his earthly affections were changed into divine love, and all the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of his Soul were engaged in the converſion of others, in preaching glad tidings, remiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to repenting ſinners, and peace to each troubled Soul: preaching the word ſo, as ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed he was poſſeſt with thoſe joys that he laboured to diſtill into others: a preacher in ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt;
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:51903:12"/> weeping ſometimes for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is Auditory, ſometimes with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem; alwayes preaching to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>imſelf like an Angel from a Cloud, though in none; carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng ſome (as <hi>Paul</hi> was) to heaven <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n holy raptures; enticing o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hers by a ſacred art and court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hip to amend their lives; and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll this with a moſt particular grace, and an unimitable fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion of ſpeaking.</p>
               <p n="12">12. Preſently after he entred into his holy Profeſſion, the King made him his Chaplain in Ordinary, and gave him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther encouragements, promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to take a care of him: And that ſummer attending his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty at <hi>Cambridge,</hi> the King was pleaſed to recommend him to be made Doctor in Divinity;
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:51903:13"/> which the Univerſity preſently granted, expreſſing a gladneſſe, they had an occaſion to entitle and write him theirs.</p>
               <p n="13">13. His abilities and indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry in his profeſſion were ſo e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent, and he ſo much loved by many perſons of quality, that within one year after his entrance into ſacred Orders, he had fourteen Advouſons of ſeveral Benefices ſent him: but he deſired rather ſome prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that might fix him in <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. And there he was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portuned by the grave Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers of <hi>Lincoln's-Inne</hi> (once the friends of his youth) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of their Lecture, which by reaſon of Mr. <hi>Gataker</hi>'s removal, was then void: of
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:51903:13"/> which he accepted: nor did he preach onely, but was an ocular direction to them, by a holy and harmleſſe converſation.</p>
               <p n="15">15. Three yeares after, by a ſpecial command from his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, Dr. <hi>Donne</hi> attended the Ambaſſadour ſent by the King, to reconcile ſome differences in <hi>Germany:</hi> and about a year after his return, the Deanary of <hi>Paul</hi>'s being vacant, the King appointed him to wait upon him at dinner the next day: and his Majeſtie being ſet down, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he eat any meat, ſaid after his pleaſant manner; Dr. <hi>Donne. I have invited you to dinner, and though you ſit not down with me, yet I will carve to you of a diſh that I know you love: you love</hi> London <hi>well; I doe therefore
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:51903:14"/> make you Dean of</hi> Paul's: <hi>Take your meat home to your ſtudy, ſay grace, and much good may it doe you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. He was once (and but once) clouded with the King's diſpleaſure, occaſioned by ſome malicious whiſperer, who aſſured the King, D. <hi>Donne</hi> had preached a Sermon that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed a diſlike of his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, particularly of his late direction, that the Evening Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures on Sundayes ſhould be turned into Catechizing. The King ſent preſently for the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor, and required his anſwer; which was ſo ſatisfactory, that the King ſaid, he was glad he reſted not under that ſuſpition: and calling ſome Lords of his Council, added with much
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:51903:14"/> earneſtneſſe; <hi>My Doctor is an honest man: and, my Lords, I was never more joyed in any thing that I have done, then in making him a Divine.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="17">17. He was made Dean in the fiftieth year of his age, and in the fifty fourth a dangerous ſickneſſe ſeized upon him, which turned to a <hi>Spotted Fea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver:</hi> But God preſerved his Spirit, keeping his intellectuals clear and perfect; and as his health encreaſed, ſo did his thankfulneſſe, teſtified in his Book of <hi>Devotions,</hi> a Compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of <hi>Holy Extaſies,</hi> occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned and appliable to the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mergencies of that ſickneſſe.</p>
               <p n="18">18. The latter part of his life was a continued ſtudy, <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turdays</hi> only excepted, which he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:51903:15"/> uſually ſpent in viſiting friend<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and reſting himſelf under the weary burthen of his weeks Meditations: And he gave himſelf this reſt, that thereby he might be refreſhed and enabled to doe the work of the day fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing, not negligently, but with courage and cheerfulneſs.</p>
               <p n="19">19. Nor was his Age onely ſo induſtrious, but in his moſt unſettled youth, he was (being in health) never known to be in bed after four of the clock in the morning, nor uſually out of his Chamber till ten; and employed that time conſtantly (if not more) in his ſtudy. The recreations of his youth were Poetry: in which he was ſo happy, as if nature with all her varieties had been made to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:51903:15"/> his great wit and high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ncy. But, in his penitential <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eares, viewing ſome of thoſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ieces looſly ſcattered in his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>outh, he wiſht they had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bortive. And yet was he not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o faln out with heavenly Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>try, as to forſake it, no not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>isdeclining age, witneſſed then <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y many divine ſonnets, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ther high, holy and harmoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>us Compoſures.</p>
               <p n="20">20. He left the Reſultance of 1400 Authours, moſt of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hem analyzed with his own hand: He left 120 Sermons al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, all writ with his own hand: A large and laborious Treatiſe called <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, wherein all the Laws violated by that Act of <hi>Self-murther</hi> are diligently ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veyed, and judiciouſly cenſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red;
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:51903:16"/> a Treatiſe written in hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> youth. All buſineſſes of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequence in this and the neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bouring Kingdomes, he abbre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viated, and kept by him for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Memorial: ſo did he the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies of divers Letters and Caſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Conſcience that had concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his friends, with his ſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. A private yearly account, wherein he computed firſt his Revenue, then his Expenſes, then what was given to th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> poor and pious uſes, laſtly what reſted for him and his: bleſſing each yeares remainder with a thankfull prayer. As, <hi>An<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> 1626.—So this year God hath bleſſed me and mine with—<hi>Multiplicatae ſunt ſuper nos miſericordiae tuae, Domine. D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Domine, ut quae ex immenſa bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitate
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:51903:16"/> tua nobis clargiri dignatus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s, in quorumcunque manus de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>enerint, in tuam ſemper <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>loriam.</hi> Amen.</p>
               <p n="21">21. He redeemed many out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>f Priſon, that lay for ſmall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ebts or for their ſees: He was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> continuall giver to poor <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>chollars, both of this and For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eign Nations: Beſides what he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ave with his own hand, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſually ſent a ſervant to all the Priſons in <hi>London,</hi> to diſtribute <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>is charity at all Feſtival times <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n the year. He gave 100 <hi>l.</hi> at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne time to a Gentleman decay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. He repaired the Chappell of his Houſe. He was a happy reconciler of differences among his friends and kindred.</p>
               <p n="22">22. In his laſt ſickneſſe he ſent for many of his moſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderable
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:51903:17"/> friends, of whom he took a ſolemn and deliberate Farewell; commending to their conſiderations ſome ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences particularly uſefull for the regulation of their lives, and diſmiſt them with a ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Benediction. At his laſt hour he ſaid, <hi>I were miſerable, if I might not die:</hi> and cloſed many periods of his faint breath with theſe words, <hi>Thy King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome come, Thy will be done:</hi> And as his laſt breath departed, and his Soul aſcended, he clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his own eyes, and then diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed his hands and body into ſuch a poſture, as required no alteration of thoſe that came to ſhroud him..</p>
               <p>Ob. ult. Mart. 1631. aetat. 59.</p>
               <byline>Out of his Life, written by <hi>Jerem. Walton.</hi>
               </byline>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="biography">
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:51903:17"/>
               <head>III. Sir W<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ILIAM COKAIN <hi>Alderman of</hi> London.</head>
               <p n="1">1. THough he were of Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of a good, of a great Eſtate, yet his poſſibility and his expectation from them did not ſlacken his own inſtuſtry; which is a Canker that eats in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, nay that hath eat up many a Family in this City, that rely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholly upon what the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath done, the Son doth nothing for himſelf. And truly it falls out too often, that he that labours not for more, does not keep his own. God imprin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in him an induſtrious diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, though ſuch hopes from his Parents might have excuſed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:51903:18"/> ſome ſlackneſſe: and God proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pered his induſtry ſo, as that when his Fathers Eſtate came to a diſtribution by Death, he needed it not.</p>
               <p n="2">2. God gave him a large and a comprehenſive under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, and with it a publick heart: and ſuch, as perchance in his way of Education, and in our narrow and contracted times, in which every man de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termines himſelf in himſelf, and ſcarce looks farther, it would be hard to find many examples of ſuch largeneſſe.</p>
               <p n="3">3. You have, I think, a phraſe <hi>of driving a Trade;</hi> and you have, I know, a practiſe <hi>of driving a way Trade,</hi> by other uſe of Money: &amp; you have loſt a man, that drove a great Trade the right way,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:51903:18"/> in making the beſt uſe of our Home-Commodity. To fetch in Wine, and Spice, and Silk, is but a drawing of Trade; the right driving of Trade, is to vent our own outward. And yet for the drawing in of that, which might juſtly ſeem moſt behovefull, <hi>i. e.</hi> of Arts and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nufactures, to be employed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our own Commodity, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the Kingdome, he did his part diligently, at leaſt, if not ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemently, if not paſſionately.</p>
               <p n="4">4. This City is a great <hi>Thea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre,</hi> and he acted great and vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous parts in it; and all well. And when he went higher (as he was often heard in Parliaments, at Council Tables, and in more private acceſſes to the late King of ever bleſſed memory) as, for
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:51903:19"/> the comprehenſion of thoſe buſineſſes, which he pretended to underſtand, no man doubts (for no man lacks arguments and evidences of his ability therein.) So, for his manner of expreſſing his intentions, and digeſting and uttering his pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſes, I have ſomtimes heard the greateſt Maſter of Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage and Iudgement, which theſe Times, or any other did, or do, or ſhall give (that good and great King of ours) ſay of him, <hi>That he never heard any man of his breeding, handle buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes more rationally, more per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinently, more elegantly, more perſwaſively.</hi> And when his purpoſe was, to do a grace ro to a Preacher of very good abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities, and good note in his own
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:51903:19"/> Chappell, I have heard him ſay, <hi>That his Language and accent, and manner of delivering him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf was like this Man.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. God multiplied his Eſtate ſo, as was fit to endow many and great Children: and he multiplied his Children ſo, both in their number and in their quality, as they were fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive a great Eſtate. God w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s with him all the way; <hi>in a pil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of fire,</hi> in the brightneſſe of proſperity; and in the <hi>pillar of clouds</hi> too, in many dark and ſad and heavy Croſſes. So great a Ship required a great ballaſt; ſo many bleſſings, many Croſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes: And he had them, and ſailed on his courſe the ſteadier for them. The <hi>Cloud</hi> as well as the <hi>Fire</hi> was a Pillar to him: His
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:51903:20"/> Croſſes as well as his Bleſſings eſtabliſht his aſſurance in God.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Lord was with him at his death too. He was ſerved with the proceſſe here in the City, but his cauſe was heard in the Countrey. Here he ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, there he languiſhed, and died there. In his ſickneſſe there, thoſe that aſſiſted him are wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of his many expreſſings of a religious &amp; a conſtant heart towards God, and of his pious joining with them, even in the holy Declaration of kneeling; then, when they, in favour of his weakneſſe, would diſwade him from kneeling. I muſt not defraud him of this Teſtimony from my ſelf, that into this place where we are now met, I have obſerved him to enter with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:51903:20"/> much reverence, and compoſe himſelf in this place with much declaration of devotion.</p>
               <p n="7">7. In his ſickneſſe he had but one dayes labour, and all the reſt were Saboths: one day he converted to buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, thus; he called his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily and Friends together; thankfully he acknowledged God's manifold Bleſſings, and his own ſins as penitently. And then, to thoſe who were to have the diſpoſing of his Eſtate, joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his Children, he recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended his ſervants, and the Poor, and the Hoſpitals, and the Priſons; which, according to his purpoſe, have been all taken into conſideration. And after this (which was his Vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction to the World) he ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:51903:21"/> alwayes loath to return to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny worldly buſineſſe.</p>
               <p n="8">8. His laſt commandement to Wife and Children, was Chriſt's laſt commandement to his Spouſe the Church, in the Apoſtles, <hi>To love one another.</hi> He bleſt them, &amp; the Eſtate de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved upon them, unto them: and by God's grace ſhall prove as true a Prophet to them in that Bleſſing, as he was to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when in entring his laſt Bed, two days before his death, he ſaid, <hi>Help me off with my earthly habit, and let me go to my laſt Bed.</hi> Where, in the ſecond night after, he ſaid, <hi>Little know ye what pain I feel this night, yet I know I ſhall have joy in the mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning:</hi> And in that morning he died.</p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:51903:21"/>
               <p>9. The form in which he implored his Saviour, was ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more towards his end, this; <hi>Chriſt Ieſus, which di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d on the Croſſe, forgive me my ſins! He, have mercy upon me!</hi> And his laſt and dying words were the repetition of the Name <hi>Ieſus.</hi> And when he had not ſtrength to utter that Name diſtinctly and perfectly, they might hear it from within him, as from a man a far off; even then, when his hollow &amp; remote naming of <hi>Ieſus,</hi> was rather a certifying of them, that he was with his <hi>Ieſus,</hi> then a Prayer that he might come unto him.</p>
               <byline>Out of his Funeral Sermon by <hi>Dr. Donne,</hi> Decemb. 23 1626.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="biography">
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:51903:22"/>
               <head>IV. Sr. THOMAS BODLEY.</head>
               <p n="1">1. I was born at <hi>Exeter</hi> in <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vonſhire</hi> 2 Mar. 1544. de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcended both by Father and Mother of worſhipful Parents. My father, in the time of Queen MARY, being noted &amp; known to be an enemy to Popery, was ſo cruelly threatned, and ſo nar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowly obſerved, by thoſe that maliced his Religion, that for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>afeguard of himſelf and my Mother, who was wholly affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted as my Father, he knew no way ſo ſecure as to fly into <hi>Germany.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. My Father fixed his abode in the City of <hi>Geneva;</hi> where, as far as I remember, the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi>
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:51903:22"/> Church conſiſted of ſome hundred perſons. I was at that time of twelve yeares of age, but through my Fathers coſt and care, ſufficiently inſtructed to become an Auditour of <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vallerius</hi> in Hebrew, of <hi>Beroal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> in Greek, of <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za</hi> in <hi>Divinity,</hi> and of ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther profeſſors in that Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity (which was newly then ere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted) beſides my domeſtick Teachers in the Houſe of <hi>Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Saracenus,</hi> a famous Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitian in that City, with whom I was boarded; where <hi>Rober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus Conſtantinus,</hi> that made the Greek <hi>Lexicon,</hi> read <hi>Homer</hi> to me.</p>
               <p n="3">3. In the firſt of Queen <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth,</hi> my Father returned, &amp; ſettled his dwelling in the City
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:51903:23"/> 
                  <hi>London.</hi> It was not long after, that I was ſent away from thence to the Univerſity of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> recommended to the teaching and tuition of Dr. <hi>Humfrey.</hi> In the year 1563 I took the degree of <hi>Batchelor of Arts;</hi> within which year I was alſo choſen <hi>Probationer</hi> of <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> Colledge, and the next year enſuing admitted <hi>Fellow.</hi> After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, in the year 1565 by ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial perſwaſion of ſome of my Fellows, and for my private exerciſe, I undertook the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick reading of a Greek Lecture in the ſame Colledge Hall, without requiring or expecting any ſtipend for it: Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it pleaſed the Fellowſhip of their own accord to allow me ſoon after four marks by the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:51903:23"/> year, and ever ſince to continue that Lecture to the Colledge.</p>
               <p n="4">4. In the year 1566 I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded <hi>Maſter of Arts,</hi> and read for that year in the School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreets natural Philoſophy. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter which time, within leſſe then three yeares ſpace, I was won by intreaty of my beſt af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected friends, to ſtand for the Proctorſhip, to which I and my Collegue were quietly elected in the year 1569, without any competition or counter-ſuit of any other. After this for a long time, I ſupplied the Office of Univerſity Oratour, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed my time in the ſtudy of ſundry faculties, without any inclination to profeſſe any one above the reſt; inſomuch as at laſt I waxed deſirous to travel
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:51903:24"/> beyond the Seas, for attaining to the knowledge of ſome ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial modern Tongues, &amp; for the encreaſe of my experience in the managing of affairs; being wholly then addicted to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy my ſelf and all my cares in the publick ſervice of the State.</p>
               <p n="5">5. After my return, in the year 1585, I was employed by the Queen to the King of <hi>Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marke,</hi> and to the <hi>German</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces: Next, to <hi>Henry</hi> the 3 King of <hi>France:</hi> After this, in 88, for the better conduct of her Highneſſe affairs in the Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces United, I was thought a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>it perſon to reſide in thoſe parts, and was ſent thereupon to the <hi>Hague</hi> in <hi>Holland;</hi> where, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Contract that had formerly paſt between her
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:51903:24"/> Highneſſe and the States, I was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dmitted for one of their Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il of Eſtate, taking place in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir aſſemblies next to Count <hi>Maurice,</hi> and yielding my ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rage in all that was propoſed. During all that time, what ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>robation was given of my <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ainfull endeavours by the Queen, Lords in <hi>England,</hi> by the States of the Country there, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y all the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Soldiery, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er it to be notified by ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>her's Relation.</p>
               <p n="6">6. I received from her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſty many comfortable Letters of her gracious acceptance of my diligence and care: and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the Lords of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il had no man more to friend, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen was the Lord Treaſurer <hi>Burleigh.</hi> For when occaſion
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:51903:25"/> had been offered of declaring his conceit as touching my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, he would alwayes tell the Queen (which I received from her ſelf and ſome other Ear<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> witneſſes) that there was not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man in <hi>England</hi> ſo meet as my ſelf to undergo the Office o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Secretary. And ſithence, his ſon, the preſent Lord Treaſurer, hath ſignifi'd unto me in private conference, that when his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther firſt intended to advanc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> him to that place, his purpoſe was withall to make me his Collegue: But that the day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly provocations of the Earl o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Eſſex</hi> were ſo bitter and ſharp a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt him, and his compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſo odious when he put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in a ballance, as he though<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> thereupon he had very grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:51903:25"/> reaſon to uſe his beſt means, to put any man out of hope of raiſing his fortune, whom the Earl with ſuch violence, to his extreme prejudice, had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured to dignifie.</p>
               <p n="7">7. When I had well conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered, how ill it did concurre with my natural diſpoſition, to become or to be counted ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a ſtickler or partaker in any publick faction; how well I was able, by Gods good bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, to live of my ſelf, if I could be contented with a competent lively hood; I reſolved thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to poſſeſſe my ſoul in peace all the reſidue of my dayes, to take my farewell of State-em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments, and ſo to retire me from the Court.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Now although after this,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:51903:26"/> by her Majeſties direction, I was often called to the Court, by the now Lord Treaſurer, then Secretary, and required by him, &amp; alſo divers times ſince, by or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from the King, to ſerve as Ambaſſadour in <hi>France,</hi> and to negotiate in other very ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable employments, yet I would not be removed from my former final reſolution; but have continued at home my retired courſe of life, which is now methinks to me as the greateſt preferment the State can afford.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This I muſt confeſſe of my ſelf, that though I did never repent me yet of my often re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſals of honourable offers, in reſpect of enriching my private Eſtate, yet ſomewhat more of
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:51903:26"/> late I have blamed my ſelf and my nicety that way, for the love that I bear to my Reverend Mother the Univerſity of <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and to the advancement of her good by ſuch kind of means as I have ſince undertaken.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Having examined what courſe I might take, I conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded at the laſt to ſet up my ſtaff at the Library door; being throughly perſwaded, that in my ſolitude and ſurceaſe from the Commonwealth a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>airs, I could not buſie my ſelf to bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter purpoſe, then by reducing that place (which then in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part lay ruined and waſt) to the publick uſe of Students.</p>
               <p n="11">11. For the effecting where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, I found my ſelf furniſhed in a competent proportion, of
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:51903:27"/> ſuch four kinds of aids, as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I had them all, there was no hope of good ſucceſſe. For without ſome kind of know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, as well in the learned mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern tongues, as in ſundry other ſorts of Scholaſtical literature; without ſome purſe ability to go through with the charge; without very great ſtore of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable friends to further the deſign, and without ſpecial good leiſure to follow ſuch a work, it could but have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a vain attempt and incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate.</p>
               <p n="12">12. But how well I have ſped in all my endeavours, and how full proviſion I have made for the benefit and eaſe of all frequenters of the Library; that which I have already performed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:51903:27"/> in ſight; That beſides, which I have given for the mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of it; and that which hereafter I purpoſe to adde, by way of enlargement to that place (for the project is caſt, and and whether I live or die, it ſhall be, God willing, put in full execution) will teſtifie ſo truly and abundantly for me, as I need not be the publiſher of the dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity and worth of mine own inſtitution. <hi>Written with mine own hand,</hi> Anno 1609. Decem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 15.</p>
               <p>Ob. <hi>Ian.</hi> 29. 1612.</p>
               <byline>Out of his Life, written by himſelf, Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted at <hi>Oxford 1647.</hi>
               </byline>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="biography">
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:51903:28"/>
               <head>V. Dr. JOHN JEWEL <hi>Biſhop of</hi> Sarum.</head>
               <p n="1">1. AS the price and happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Aurelius Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinus</hi> his Labours and Works, the induſtrious vigilancy of <hi>Gregory,</hi> the heavenly gifts of <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> the divine ſpirit of <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> the golden mouth of <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> the ſweet vein of <hi>Lactantius,</hi> the ſhining ſtyle of <hi>Fulgentius,</hi> are very conſpicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous in their names; ſo here Grace in <hi>Iohn,</hi> and eminent Perfection in <hi>Iewell.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. He was born of virtuous and religious Parents, in the County of <hi>Devon</hi> (Anno 1522. May 24) a fertile ſoil of many
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:51903:28"/> good Wits, and two other moſt eminent, of the ſame Colledge after him, Dr. <hi>Reynolds</hi> and Mr. <hi>Hooker.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. His ſingular promptneſſe of Wit and Induſtry accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with ingenuity and mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty, begat an exceeding love of him in his Maſter <hi>Bowin;</hi> whom afterwards, when he was Biſhop, he forgat not, but moſt highly eſteemed and bountifully rewarded all <hi>Bowins</hi> for his Maſters ſake.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He was ſent to <hi>Oxford</hi> at the age of thirteen, and taken by Mr. <hi>Parkhurſt</hi> of <hi>Merton</hi> Colledge to be his Poſtmaſter, who perceiving his capacity let fall a prophetical ſpeech of him; <hi>Surely</hi> Paul's <hi>Croſſe will one day ring of this boy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:51903:29"/>5. From <hi>Merton</hi> Colledge he was tranſplanted into <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus-Chriſti,</hi> and there choſen before all his Seniors to read the <hi>Humanity</hi> Lecture; which he did with ſuch diligence and facility, that many came from divers other Colledges to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold <hi>Rhetorick</hi> ſo richly ſet forth; among others, his Tutor Mr. <hi>Parkhurſt</hi> of <hi>Merton,</hi> who after the Lecture ended, ſaluted <hi>Iewell</hi> with this Diſtick.</p>
               <lg>
                  <l>Olim Diſcipulus mihi, chare <hi>Juelle,</hi> ſuiſti:</l>
                  <l>Nune ero Diſcipulus, te renucn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c, tuus.</l>
               </lg>
               <p n="6">6. So induſtrious he was, that for the greateſt part of the day he did himſelf in his Study, and ſo much recalled his ſenſes from all external objects, that <hi>Chryſippus</hi>-like, he needed a <hi>Meliſſa</hi> to put him in mind of
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:51903:29"/> his meat. His onely Recreati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons from ſtudies were ſtudious being either in inſtructing his Scholars, or diſputing, or me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation.</p>
               <p n="7">7. As for his life and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in this ſlippery age, take the teſtimony of an adverſary (equall to a general conſent) the Dean of the Colledge: <hi>I ſhould love thee,</hi> Iewell (ſaid he) <hi>if thou wert not a</hi> Zuinglian; <hi>In thy Faith I hold thee an Heretick, but ſurely in thy life thou art an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. <hi>Peter Martyr,</hi> in the time of <hi>Edward</hi> 6. being called over, and appointed by the King Profeſſor of Divinity in <hi>Oxford,</hi> our <hi>Iewell</hi> was his Auditour, copied out his Lectures &amp; Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, was his Notary in that
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:51903:30"/> tumultuary diſputation abou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the Real Preſence, and in tim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> became moſt intimate with him.</p>
               <p n="9">9. In thoſe dayes of Peace he was noted alſo for an Orati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in <hi>Engliſh</hi> pronounced in the Colledge in praiſe of the Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, and two S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rmons in Latin <hi>Ad Clerum,</hi> and for his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at <hi>Sunning well,</hi> whither he went on Foot at leaſt every fortnight.</p>
               <p n="10">10. At his departure from the Colledge in the concluſion of his Speech, Pardon me, good Sirs, ſaid he, if it do grieve me to leave the place where I have been brought up, where I have lived hitherto, where I have been in ſome place and reckoning. But why do I ſtick
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:51903:30"/> to kill my heart with one word? Alaſs that I muſt ſpeak it, as with grief I muſt; <hi>Valcant stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia, valeant haec tecta, valcat ſc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des cultiſsimalitcrarum, valcat jucundiſsimus conſpectus veſtri, valetejuvenes, valcte ſoc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i vale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tefratres, valcte oculi mei, valcte omnes, valcte.</hi> Thus he burſt out of his Speech, and his hearers burſt out into tears.</p>
               <p n="11">11. After his expulſion, la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable in the manner, but glorious in the cauſe, he ſtayed himſelf at <hi>Broadgates</hi> Hall; where Fame of his Learning drew many Scholars unto him. In the mean time, the Colledge, by their unjuſt ejection of him, were puniſhed not onely with loſſe, but with diſgrace: For, when the Dean boaſted of their
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:51903:31"/> care in preſerving the Colledge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſtments and Treaſure, the Arch-Deacon of <hi>Oxford</hi> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Ye have done ſo indeed, but ye have wilfully lost one Orna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and great Treaſure, far more precious then any of theſe:</hi> alluding to the ſaying of <hi>Corne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> Mother of the <hi>Gracchi, H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt ornamenta mea,</hi> ſhewing her Sons to another Lady, that ſhewed her pearles and coſtly attire.</p>
               <p n="12">12. At this time the Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity choſe him for their Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratour; in whoſe name he cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſly penned a gratulatory Letter to Queen MARY, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting of exclamations of grief for the Funeralls of King ED<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>WARD, and acclamations of joy for her happy Coronation.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:51903:31"/> By which Letter, it ſeemeth, Mr. <hi>Iewell</hi> &amp; others conceived good hope, that Queen MARY would not altogether change Religion. Which hope ſtayed him ſo long in <hi>Oxford,</hi> till the Inquiſition caught him, and ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged ſubſcription under pain of preſcription and torture.</p>
               <p n="13">13. Here <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>well</hi> brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſtrait, having no other Counſellours, but horrour without and frailty within, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to them, <hi>Do you deſire to ſee my hand, and will you try how well I can write?</hi> took the Pen and haſtily writ his name, whereby he ſeemed to approve ſome Articles of Popery: But this ſubſcribing procured not his ſafety; for he had been taken again, had he not by Gods pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:51903:32"/> gone a wrong way to <hi>London,</hi> and ſo eſcaped their hands that waited for him in the uſual way: as St. <hi>Auſtin</hi> by the errour of his guide eſcaped the <hi>Donatiſts.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. Pope <hi>Marcellinus</hi> waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed out his ſtian of Idolatry with tears of repentance and blood of Martyrdome: <hi>Cranmer</hi> pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged the polluted hand that had ſubſcribed, with fire, before he was made an Holocauſt. <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gen</hi> and <hi>Iewell</hi> repealed their publick ſubſcription by publick confeſſion and contrition. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he came to <hi>Frankford,</hi> he made an excellent Sermon, and confeſſed his fall, and was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived there and embraced as amoſt dear Brother, nay, as an Angel of God.</p>
               <p n="15">
                  <pb n="53" facs="tcp:51903:32"/>15. From <hi>Frankford</hi> he was invited by the kind Letters of <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> to <hi>Argentine,</hi> where he converſed with <hi>Grin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dal, Sandys, Cheek,</hi> and other <hi>Engliſh</hi> Exiles for Religion; and aſſiſted <hi>Martyr</hi> in the Edition of his Commentary upon <hi>Iud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges:</hi> In whoſe houſe he ſpent the greateſt part of his time, as a Companion of his ſtudies, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavouring alſo ſometimes to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>poſe the contentions among his Brethren, ſomtimes to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort them in their afflictions, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating uſually theſe words, <hi>Haec non dur abunt aetatem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. After his return, he was ſent for to a Diſputation at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter.</hi> The <hi>Theſes</hi> were, 1. <hi>That it is repugnant to the Word of God, and cuſtome of the Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitive
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:51903:33"/> Church, that Church-ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice and Liturgy ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in an unknown Tongue. 2. That every Church hath power to alter Rites and Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies for her better edification. 3. That the propitiatory ſacrifice of the Maſſe for quick and dead hath no warrant in the Word of God.</hi> But the Diſputation was broke off, &amp; Religion ſettled by the Parliament.</p>
               <p n="17">17. <hi>Iewell</hi> was appointed for the Viſitation of the <hi>Weſtern</hi> Churches: and ſo it fell out ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fitly, that he preſented his firſt labours in the Miniſtry af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his return, in <hi>Devonſhire</hi> and parts adjacent; there firſt break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the bread of life, where firſt he received the breath of life. After which Viſitation, he was
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:51903:33"/> conſecrated Biſhop of <hi>Sarisbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> with much reluctancy, often repeating the Apoſtle's words, <hi>Qui deſiderat Epiſcopatum, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderat opus.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="18">18. And ſurely, if ever to any, then unto him was his Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhoprick a continual work: ſuch was his care, that his Church ſhould ſuſtain no loſſe; ſuch his pains in Governing and in Preadhing, that abuſes might not grow by the negligence or corruption of Officials. He ſate often himſelf with his Chancel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, and was preſident in his Conſiſtory: where though he were a ſtrict executor of Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical Lawes, yet no doubt he temper'd ſeverity with that lenity which he exhorted B. <hi>Parkhurſt</hi> to in a certain Letter:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:51903:34"/> 
                  <hi>Let your Chancellour</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>be harder, but you eaſier; let him wound, but do you heal; let him lance, doe you plaiſter. Wiſecle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mency will doe more good, then rigid ſeverity: One man may move more with an Engine, then ſix with the force of their hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="19">19. When his friends ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſhed him to lighten his over-heavy burden of ruling &amp; inſtructing every particular Church in his Dioceſe, by Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutes and Coadjutors, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed; <hi>Vnlearned men can doe me no good, and to the Learned I can doe no good: I have no Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefices in my gift to maintain them:</hi> Capon <hi>my predeceſſour hath devoured all.</hi> This <hi>Capon,</hi> unhappily underſtanding that of St. <hi>Paul,</hi> as one is ſaid to have
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:51903:34"/> read it, <hi>Qui deſider at Epiſcopa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum bonum, opes deſider at,</hi> made havock of all the good Livings in his Dioceſe, enriching himſelf, &amp; leaving the Biſhoprick poor.</p>
               <p n="20">20. In all the time of his Biſhoprick, ſcarce any year paſſed, which was not made noble and illuſtrious by ſome work of his. The year 1560. began with his noble challenge at <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Croſs<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> and ended with his confutation of Dr. <hi>Cole.</hi> His Apology, begun in the year 61, and per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ected 62, was made ſo much of by all Proteſtants, that it was tranſlated almoſt into all Tongues. The years 64 and 65, were renowned for his and Mr. <hi>Harding</hi>'s contentions a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the forenamed challenge: In which time alſo he was ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:51903:35"/> created Doctor, and bare the part of a Moderatour in thoſe famous Acts, conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with a divine ſpeech of Queen ELIZABETH: His Defenſe fell in the years 66 and 67. After which time divers Learned Books were dedicated to him by <hi>Martyr, Bullinger</hi> and others: and himſelf inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded divers other excellent Works; but death prevented the birth of them,</p>
               <p n="20">20. He recreated himſelf at his meals (a Chapter being firſt read) with School-diſputes of young Boyes, whom he main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at his Table. After din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, his doors and eares were open to all ſuits and cauſes. After buſineſſes diſpatcht, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tired to his ſtudy: About nine
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:51903:35"/> he called all his Servants to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count, how they had ſpent the day; and after prayers admoni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed them accordingly: Then to his ſtudy again, oft-times till midnight; and ſo to Bed: wherein after ſome part of an Authour read unto him by the Gentleman of his Bed chamber, commending himſelf to the protection of his Saviour, he took his reſt.</p>
               <p n="21">21. His memory was admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, raiſed by Art to the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt pitch. For he could repeat faithfully any thing he had pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, as he had penned it, after once reading; and therefore uſually at the ringing of the Bell, began to commit his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons to heart. Many barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous hard names and ſtrange
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:51903:36"/> words, after once or twice reading and ſhort meditating, he could repeat backward and forward. This Art of Memory he taught his old Tutor Mr. <hi>Parkhurst</hi> beyond the Sea; ſo that in a ſhort time, ſpending but one hour in a day at it, he learned all the Goſpel back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward and forward by this arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial Memory.</p>
               <p n="22">22. His continual labours brought his body ſo low, that as he rode abroad to preach, a Gentleman adviſed him to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn home for his health ſake, ſaying, it was better the people ſhould want one Sermon, then be deprived of ſuch a Preacher; but he replyed, <hi>It becomes a Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop to dye in the Pulpit.</hi> To one weeping at his bed ſide, he uſed
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:51903:36"/> the words of <hi>Ambroſe; I have not ſo lived, that I am aſhamed to live longer; neither doe I fear to die, becauſe we have a merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Lord.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="23">23. In his Will, he conſidered his Brother and friends with ſome kind remembrances, but beſtowed the reſt moſt li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berally upon his ſervants, ſchol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and the poor of <hi>Sarum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="24">24. Before his death, he called his houſhold about him, and after an expoſition of the Lord's Prayer, among others uſed theſe words; <hi>It was my Prayer alwayes to almightie God, ſince I had any underſtanding, that I might honour his Name with the ſacrifice of my fleſh, and confirm his Truth with the oblation of this my body unto
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:51903:37"/> death in the defenſe thereof; which ſeeing he hath not gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted me in this, yet I ſome what rejoice and ſolace my ſelf, that it is worn away and exhauſted in the labours of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y holy Calling.</hi> Mr. <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>dley,</hi> the Steward of his Houſe, ſhut his eyes in the year of our Lord 1571. <hi>Sept.</hi> 22. a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout three of the clock in the afternoon.</p>
               <p>Anno aetat. 50.</p>
               <byline>Out of his Life, prefixed to his-Works.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="biography">
               <head>VI. Mr. GEORGE HERBERT.</head>
               <p n="1">1. BEing nobly born, and a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eminently endued with gifts of the mind; and having by induſtry and happy educati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:51903:37"/> perfected them to a great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellency (whereof his Fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> &amp; his Oratourſhip in the Univerſity; together with that knowledge the Kings Court had taken of him, are eviden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces:) quitting all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties that he had for worldly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment, he betook himſelf to the Sanctuary, chooſing rather to ſerve at God's Altar, then to ſeek the honour of State-em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments.</p>
               <p n="2">2. To teſtifie his indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dency upon all others, and to quicken his diligence in the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry, he uſed in his ordinary ſpeech, when he made menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the bleſſed name of Ieſus Chriſt, to adde, My Maſter.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Next God, he loved that
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:51903:38"/> which God himſelf hath mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified above all things, <hi>i. e.</hi> his Word: ſo as he hath been heard to make ſolemn Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>That he would not part with one leaf thereof for the whole World, if it were offered him in exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">4. His obedience and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity to the Church and the diſcipline thereof, was ſingular<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly remarkable. Though he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded in private devotions, yet went he every morning and evening with his Family to the Church; and by his example, exhortations and encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments drew the greater part of his Pariſhioners to accompany him dayly in the publick cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of Divine ſervice.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As for worldly matters,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:51903:38"/> his love and eſteem to them was ſo little, as no man can more ambitiouſly ſeek, then he did earneſtly endeavour the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of an Eccleſiaſticall dignity, which he was poſſeſſor of. But God permitted not the accompliſhment of his deſire, having ordained him his Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, for r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>edifying the Church belonging thereunto.</p>
               <p n="6">6. With the remembrance whereof, as of an eſpecial good work, when a friend went a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout to comfort him on his death bed, he made anſwer; <hi>It is a good work, if it be ſprinkled with the blood of Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. We conclude with his <hi>Motto,</hi> with which he uſed to conclude all things, that might ſeem to tend any way to his own
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:51903:39"/> honour; <hi>Leſſe then the least of Gods mercies.</hi>
               </p>
               <byline>Out of the Preface to his Sacred Poems.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="biography">
               <head>VII. Dr. JAMES USSHER <hi>Arch-Biſhop of</hi> Armagh.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HE had conſtantly prayers in his Family four times a day. At ſix in the morning, and eight at night, they were ſuch, wherein the gifts of thoſe who were his Chaplains were exerciſed: but before dinner &amp; ſupper in the Chappell, the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turgy</hi> was conſtantly obſerved<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> which he had in eſtimation to his laſt.</p>
               <p n="2">2. A form of Prayer, not onely by way of direction, but
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:51903:39"/> punctually compoſed, he ever <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udged to conduce to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ik benefit, eſpecially in the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of Baptiſm and the Communion: as well for the ſhnning and preventing the diſorder and ſcandalous con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſion found in ſome mens per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of them, as the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ying of an unity and unanimi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y among us, which St. <hi>Paul</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>refers as the more excellent way, before the vanity of all ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall gifts whatſoever. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning which, he wiſhed the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>udgement of <hi>Calvin</hi> (in his Letter to the Protectour) were more known then it is, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his eſteem with ſuch as have oppoſed it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. For Ordination, or an ordained Miniſtry, ſuch was his
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:51903:40"/> judgement of the neceſſity of it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that he took it to be a Fund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mental, and one of thoſe pri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of Chriſtian Doctri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> (<hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 2.) called, <hi>laying on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> hands.</hi> The great neglect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> which he much lamented, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fearing it would prove to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the undermining the founda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of our Church; which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Cartwright,</hi> in his Comment<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry upon the place, confirms t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the full, and in a higher expre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, as if it were the overthro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of Chriſtianity.</p>
               <p n="4">4. What his judgement was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the uſe of the Lords Prayer, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> practiſe ſhewed it in the co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant concluding of his Pray before Sermon with it. And h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> approbation of that geſture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> kneeling at the Communio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:51903:40"/> as often apparent before ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> witneſſes.</p>
               <p n="5">5. For Confirmation of chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>en (which <hi>Calvin, Beza</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ers much commend, &amp; wiſh it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ere reſtored) he was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng in obſervation of it, as an an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ent laudable cuſtome. And <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s Benediction was ſeconded <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ith good and ſpirituall inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ion, that ſtuck to the children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen they came to further years.</p>
               <p n="6">6. The Church Catechiſm, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſpiſed by ſome for its plaineſs, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e thought therefore to be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ore profitable to the vulgar, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd gave order it ſhould every <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ords day in the afternoon be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xplained.</p>
               <p n="7">7. He was indeed, as <hi>Eraſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>us</hi> ſaith of St. <hi>Auſtin, Vivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>um quodda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> exemplar Epiſcopi,
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:51903:41"/> omnibus virtutu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> numeris abſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi> And I wiſh all that have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> reverent opinion of him, would ſhow it, in taking his ſpirit o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Moderation for their Copy.</p>
               <byline>
                  <hi>Out of</hi> Dr. Bernard.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="biography">
               <head>VIII Mr. JOHN HALES.</head>
               <p n="1">1. MR <hi>Iohn Hales,</hi> ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time (Fellow of <hi>Merto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Colledge &amp;) Greek Profeſſou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Univerſity of <hi>Oxford,</hi> long Fellow of <hi>Eton</hi> Colledge, and at laſt alſo Prebendary of <hi>Windſore,</hi> was a man, I think, of as great a ſharpneſſe, quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſubtilty of Wit, as e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver this, or perhaps any Nation bred.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:51903:41"/>2. His induſtry did ſtrive, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were poſſible, to equall the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>argeneſs of his capacity: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y he became as great a Maſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> polite, various and univerſal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earning, as ever yet converſt with Books.</p>
               <p n="3">3. Proportionate to his Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng was his Meditation, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>urniſhed him with a judgement <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eyond the vulgar reach of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>an, built upon unordinary Notions, raiſed out of ſtrange <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>bſervations and comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive thoughts within himſelf. So that he really was a moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igious example of an acute &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iercing Wit, of a vaſt and illi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mited knowledge, of a ſevere <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd profound judgement.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Yet, had he never under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tood a Letter, he had other.
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:51903:42"/> Ornaments ſufficient to endear him. For he was of a nature (as we ordinarily ſpeak) ſo kind, ſo ſweet, ſo courting all mankind; of an affability ſo prompt, ſo ready to receive all conditions of men, that I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it were as eaſie a task for any one to become ſo know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ſo obliging.</p>
               <p n="5">5. As a Chriſtian, none more ever acquainted with the nature of the Goſpel, becauſe none more ſtudious of the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of it, or more curious in the ſearch; which being ſtrengthned by thoſe great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages before mentioned, could not prove other then highly effectual.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He took indeed to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a liberty of judging, not of
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:51903:42"/> others, but for himſelf: and if ever any man might be allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in theſe matters to judge, it was he, who had ſo long, ſo much, ſo advantageouſly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider'd; &amp; which is more, never had the leaſt worldly deſign in his determinations.</p>
               <p n="7">7. He was not only moſt truly and ſtrictly juſt in his ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>cular tranſactions, moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emplarily meek and humble, notwithſtanding his perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but beyond all example charitable, giving unto all, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving nothing but his Books, to continue his learning and himſelf: which, when he had before digeſted, he was forced at laſt to feed upon, at the ſame time the happieſt and moſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortunate <hi>helluo</hi> of Books; the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:51903:43"/> grand example of Learning, and of the Envy and contempt which followeth it.</p>
               <p n="8">8. While he lived none was ever more ſollicited and urged to write, and thereby truly to teach the world, then he; none ever ſo reſolved (pardon the expreſſion, ſo obſtinate) againſt it. His facile and courteous na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture learnt only not to yield to that ſollicitation. And yet he cannot be accuſed for hiding of his Talent, being ſo commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicative, that his Chamber was a Church, and his Chair a Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Onely that there migh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſome Taſte continue of him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſome of his Remains were col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, ſuch as he could not but write, and ſuch as when
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:51903:43"/> written, were out of his power to deſtroy. Theſe conſiſt of two parts, of <hi>Sermons,</hi> and of <hi>Letters:</hi> and each of them proceeded from him upon reſpective obligations. The <hi>Letters,</hi> though written by himſelf, yet were wholly in the power of that Honourable perſon to whom they were ſent, and by that means they were preſerv'd. The <hi>Sermons</hi> preached on ſeveral occaſions were ſnatcht from him by his friends, and in their hands, the Copies were continued, or by tranſcription diſperſt.</p>
               <p n="10">10. As to thoſe <note place="margin">Cut of Mr. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringtons Letter.</note> Letters written from the Synod of <hi>Dort,</hi> take notice that in his younger days he was a <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> and even
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:51903:44"/> then when he was employed at that Synod, and at the well preſſing Io, 3. 16. by <hi>Epiſcopus, There I bid Iohn Calvin Good Night,</hi> as he has after told me. I have drawn in my mind the model of his Life: but I am like Mr. <hi>Hales</hi> in this, which was one of his defects, not to pen any thing, till I needs muſt.</p>
               <byline>Out of <hi>Dr. Pearſons</hi> Preface to his Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Remains.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="biography">
               <head>IX. R. EVELYN.</head>
               <div type="biography_proper">
                  <p n="1">1. HE was taught to pray as ſoon as he could ſpeak, and he was taught to read as ſoon as he could pray. At three years old, he read any character or letter whatſoever uſed in out printed books, and within a
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:51903:44"/> little time after any tolerable writing hand; and had gotten by heart, before he was five years of age, ſeven or eight hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Latine and Greek words, together with their Genders and Declenſions.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. His Promptitude in this nature was prodigious, ſo that I have been ready to cry out, <hi>Horrori mihi est hoc ingenium.</hi> So infatiable were his deſires of knowledge, that upon a time hearing one diſcourſe of <hi>Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> and <hi>Plautus,</hi> and being told (upon his enquiry con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe Authours) that the books were too difficult for him, he wept for very grief and would hardly be pacified.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. To tell you how exactly he read French, how much of
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:51903:45"/> it he ſpake and underſtood, were to let you only know, that his Mother did inſtruct him without any confuſion to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eſt. Thus he learned a Gate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme &amp; many prayers, &amp; read divers things in that La<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>guage.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. His uſual Recreations were eſpecially the <hi>Apologu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s</hi> of <hi>Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſop:</hi> moſt of which he could ſo readily recount, with divers o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſtories, as you would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire from whence he produc'd them. But he was never with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſome book or other in his hand. He often delighted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in reciting of Poems and Sentences, ſome whereof he had in Greek fragments of Comedies, divers verſes out of <hi>Herbert;</hi> and amongſt the <hi>Pſalmes,</hi> his beloved and often
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:51903:45"/> repeated, <hi>Ecce quam bonum!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5. I might adde the incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable ſweetneſſe of his coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance and eyes, the clean fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick of his body, and prett<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> addreſſes: how eaſily he forgot injuries, when at any time I would break and croſs his paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, by ſometimes interrupt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his enjoyments in the midſt of ſome delicious things which allured him. But above all, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treamly conſpicuous was his affection to his younger bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, with whoſe impertinen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies he would continually bear, ſaying, <hi>he was but a child and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood no better.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. There are better things behind, and thoſe are his early Piety and how ripe he was for God. Never did this child lye
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:51903:46"/> in bed (by his good will) lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then ſix or ſeaven, Winter or Summer: and the firſt thing he did being up, was to ſay his French prayers, &amp; our Church-Catechiſme; after breakfaſt that ſhort Latine prayer, which having encountred at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of our <hi>Lilies</hi> Grammar, he had learned by heart with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any knowledge or injun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of mine.</p>
                  <p n="7">7. Wonderfull was it to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the Chapters which him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf would chooſe, and the Pſalms and Verſes that he would apply upon occaſions, and as in particular he did to ſome that were ſick in my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily a little before him; bid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them to <hi>conſider the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt, how bitter they
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:51903:46"/> were and how willingly he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured them.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8. The laſt time he was at Church (which was as I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member at <hi>Greenwich</hi>) at his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn I asked him, what he brought away from the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon? He replyed, that he had remembred two good things, <hi>Bonum gratiae,</hi> and <hi>Bonum glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riae:</hi> which expreſſions were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed uſed, though I did not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve he had minded them.</p>
                  <p n="9">9. When about Chriſtmas a kinſman of his related to us by the fire ſide ſome paſſages of the preſumptuous faſting of certain <hi>Enthuſiaſts</hi> about <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> whilſt we were expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome admiration at the paſſage, <hi>That,</hi> ſayes the Child, <hi>is no ſuch wonder; for it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:51903:47"/> Man ſhall not live by bread alone, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="10">10 When the Lords day fortnight before he dyed, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated to me our Church-Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, he told me, <hi>That he now perceived that his Godfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers were diſengaged; for that ſince he himſelf did now under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what his Duty was, it would be required of him and not of them for the future.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="11">11. How divinely did this pious Infant ſpeak of his being weary of this troubleſome world (into which he was ſcarcely entred) and whilſt he lay ſick, of his deſires to go to heaven, that the Angels might conveigh him into <hi>Abrahams</hi> boſome, paſſionately perſwad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thoſe that tended him to die with him.</p>
                  <p n="12">
                     <pb n="83" facs="tcp:51903:47"/>12. The day before he took his leave of us, he call'd to me, and pronounced it very ſober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: <hi>Father,</hi> ſayes he, <hi>You have often told me, that you would give me your houſe and your land, your books, and all your fine things: but I tell you, I ſhall have none of them; you will leave them all to my brother.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="13">13. That very morning, not many hours before he fell into that ſleep which was his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>laſt, being in the midſt of his Paroxyſm, he called to me, and asked me, <hi>whether he ſhould not offend, if in the extremity of his pain, he mentioned ſo often the name of God, calling for eaſe?</hi> And, <hi>whether God would accept his prayers if he did not hold his hands out of bed in the poſture of
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:51903:48"/> praying?</hi> Which when I had pacified him about, he prayed, till his prayers were turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to eternal praiſes.</p>
                  <byline>Out of his Fathers Epiſtle before Chryſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome, of Education.</byline>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Grot.</hi> ad Patrem.</bibl>
                     <q>Carere liberis durum non eſt, niſi his qui habuerunt.</q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="epitaph">
                  <argument>
                     <p>I ſhall onely adde the Epitaph written upon this admirable Child by that excellent Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar and his kinſman. Mr. <hi>Chriſtopher Waſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </argument>
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:51903:48"/>
                  <head>EPITAPHIUM. R. EVELYN. I. F.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Quieſeit hoe ſub ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>more,</l>
                     <l>Unà quieſeit quicquid eſt amabile,</l>
                     <l>Patres quod optent, aut quod orbi lugeant.</l>
                     <l>Genas inſontes non, ut ante, riſus</l>
                     <l>Lepore condit ampl us.</l>
                     <l>Morum venuſtus, quanta paucis contigit</l>
                     <l>Deſidetatur omnibus.</l>
                     <l>Linguae, Latina. G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>llica,</l>
                     <l>Quas imbibit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>um lacte materno, ta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ent,</l>
                     <l>Tentarat A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tes, A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tiumque principis</l>
                     <l>Pi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>tatis elementa hauſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>at.</l>
                     <l>Lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>is inhaeſit improbo labore,</l>
                     <l>Ut ſola mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s divelleret,</l>
                     <l>Quid indoles, quid diſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>iplina, quid labor</l>
                     <l>Poſſint, ab uno diſceres.</l>
                     <l>Puer ſtupendus! qualis! lie eſſet ſenex,</l>
                     <l>Si fata vitae ſubminiſtraſſent iter!</l>
                     <l>Sed aliter eſt viſum Deo.</l>
                     <l>Correptus ille febricula levi jacet:</l>
                     <l>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>acent tot unà ſpes parentum.</l>
                     <l>Vixit An. V. M. V. III. ſuper D.</l>
                     <l>Eheu! Delicias breves!</l>
                     <l>Quicquid placet mortale non placet diu,</l>
                     <l>Quicquid placet mortale ne placeat nimis</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="biography">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:51903:49"/>
               <head>D. ARTHUR LAKE, Biſhop of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. THis Holy man was nour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed up from his tender age in the exerciſes of true pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and in the ſtudies of various and exquiſite learning, and in his riper years advanced to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers eminent places of dignity in the Church, not by any am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitious ſuit or ſeeking of his own, but by the ſpecial provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of God, beyond his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation or deſire raiſed to the height of Epiſcopal Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He was firſt placed a Child in the famous School of <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> thence elected Fellow in New Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> and after Fellow in the Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:51903:49"/> neer <hi>Wincheſter:</hi> thence again recalled by the conſpiring Votes of that numerous Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty to the Warden-ſhip of New Colledge. Afterward, prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red firſt to the prefecture of the Hoſpital of S. <hi>Croſſes</hi> neer <hi>Win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chester,</hi> then to the Deanry of the Cathredral Church of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter.</hi> And laſtly to the Biſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rick of <hi>Bath</hi> and <hi>Wells</hi> where he dyed.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He continued the ſame in his Rocket, which he had been in his Scholars Gown, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving ſo well ſtudied <hi>Humility</hi> (the baſis of all vertue) in his younger years, that in the whole courſe of his life there was no tumour of pride appeared, but as well in his actions as in his ſpeeches, equalling himſelf
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:51903:50"/> with the loweſt; not withſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the many temptations he had both from the eminency of his place &amp; excellency of his parts to do &amp; ſpeak otherwiſe. From this did proceed that ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular <hi>Affability</hi> and eaſineſſe of acceſſe, which he ever retained to all ſorts of men, &amp; to thoſe of his own Coat eſpecially: ſo that no man can ſay, he was ever ſleighted, or ſuperciliouſly uſed by him.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Adde hereunto his rare <hi>Tranquillity and Contentedneſſe of minde.</hi> He retained the ſame temper in all the alterations of his eſtate; So that whatſoever outwardly befell him, either to the better or the worſer part, he ſeemed very little to be affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, ſurely nothing diſquieted
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:51903:50"/> there withall. A ſtrange ſerenity of mind in him; whereof I take it alſo to have been a good ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument, that (as I have often heard him ſay) ſo long as he was in perfect health of his body, he did never dream.</p>
               <p n="5">5. His <hi>Temperance</hi> was ſuch, that at the greateſt and beſt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed tables, whereat the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of his place required his preſence, his feeding was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly upon one diſh and that none of the daintieſt. And when he was not hindred by reſort of ſtrangers unto him, he faſted uſually four times in the week from his ſupper, and ſpent that time in framing ſome Meditation or other upon a piece of Holy Scripture.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Unleſſe it were in the
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:51903:51"/> company of Scholars, and in ſuch ingenious &amp; pleaſant Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes as are incident thereto (wherein he would ſometimes expreſſe much freedome of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent mirth) a man could not obſerve, that he took much delight in any worldly thing whatſoever: an evident argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that his intellectual part had the predominancy over his ſenſual, or rather indeed that Grace ruled them both, and that the <hi>Man</hi> in him was ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinate to the <hi>Christian.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. As he had been alwayes <hi>liberal,</hi> from the time he had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing to give; ſo upon the increaſe of his fortunes he im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved that virtue, even to a kind of <hi>Magnificence.</hi> And though his forwardneſſe in gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:51903:51"/> never let him ſtay till his purſe was full, ſo that he attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not to the doing of any pom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pous work: yet his ordinary largeſſe to the poor at his Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e and in the ſtreets; his Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions to pious works of all ſorts; his Exhibitions to poor Scholars both abroad and in the Univerſity; his encreaſing the allowance of the poor Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of S. <hi>Croſs;</hi> his maintan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of two Lectures in New Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> one for the Hebrew Tongue, another for the Mathematicks; (A great part of his books, he diſpoſed to the Library of New Colledge by a deed of gift, divers years before his death, reſerving the uſe of them onely for his life time.) his leading the way to the
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:51903:52"/> founding of a Library at <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,</hi> and another at <hi>Wells,</hi> are ſufficient inſtances of his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Bounty.</p>
               <p n="8">8. His <hi>Contempt of VVealth</hi> I may reckon as a part of his Magnanimity. I dare ſay, that in all Elections of Scholars, Collation of Orders, and Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices, Diſpoſitions of Offices, and Grants of Colledge and Church-Leaſes, that paſſed through his hands (as there paſſed in his time very many) he never fouled them with the leaſt touch of a <hi>Gehaz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'s</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, which integrity of his, together with his open<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>hand<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>dedneſſe and Houſe-keeping, were the onely Cauſes that he left no greater Eſtate behind him.</p>
               <p n="9">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:51903:52"/>9. His <hi>Ability to teach,</hi> as it was very great, ſo did it never appear more, then after he was a Biſhop. For though the acts of government alone may ſeem ſufficient to take up a man in that place: yet he never ceas'd to adorn the Pulpit with his no leſs frequent and aſſiduous, then learned and pious labours. Witneſſe his ordinary preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Cathedral Church of <hi>VVells;</hi> his frequent excurſions into the Pariſhes adjoyning; and indeed his leaving of no place, where he came, if it were a fit time of preaching, unſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed. Beſides all which his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Diſcourſes were in one kind or other as good as Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures to thoſe that heard them.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Beſides his ordinary Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:51903:53"/> hours, which he ſaw due<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and by all frequented; he cauſed many of his houſhold to aſſiſt every morning at the ſix a clock prayers in the Cathredral' Church adjoyning: He never ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e down at his meals, but he had, according to the ancient faſhion of Biſhops, a Chapter of the Bible read by one whom he kept for that purpoſe; and laſtly, at the cloſe of the night, he called his whole Family in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his ordinary Dining room, and there, in his own perſon, moſt devoutly commended them by his prayers to Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty God.</p>
               <p n="11">11. He never conferred ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Orders upon any perſon, whom he did not firſt examine ſtrictly according to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nons
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:51903:53"/> of the Church; neither did he truſt herein any Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain or other Deputy, but him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf perſonally performed the office. And as he was provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to plant a good Miniſtrie in his Dioceſs, ſo was he no leſs carefull to cheriſh thoſe who were already planted. The moſt eminent among them for pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and learning, he did not only uſe moſt familiarly, but ſtudied to draw them neareſt to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf by providing them of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bends in his Church: and to the weaker ſort of them, he ſpared not to give his advice and dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions upon all occaſions, how they might enable themſelves for the better diſcharge of their Calling.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In the exerciſe of the
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:51903:54"/> Diſcipline of the Church, he carried himſelf ſo, that by his own practice he wrought a great reverence thereof, even in thoſe who were otherwiſe not well affected thereunto. For when any enormous Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fender was cenſured in his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory, whoſe puniſhment and penance was fit ſhould be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed in the Cathedral Church, as inceſtuous perſons, notorious adulterers, notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſchiſmaticks or the like; Himſelf was uſually the prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher at ſuch times: and this he did often and upon divers oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions, and in ſuch his Sermons did ſo open the grievouſneſſe of thoſe Offences, and the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of the Cenſurers and Diſcipline of the Church, as for
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:51903:54"/> the moſt part wrought great Contrition in the parties puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed; and after Sermon before the whole Congregation, him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf gave them Abſolution. All which he performed with that gravity, learning and power, as gave great comfort to all, and bred, no doubt, a general reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence and awe of the Cenſures and Authority of the Church.</p>
               <p n="13">13. His Trienniall Viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, he alwayes kept in his own perſon; and kept them ſo, that (to ſay no more) he was ever welcome where he came. They reſorted and flockt to him in every place, <hi>tanquam ad ſalutare &amp; beneficum ſidus;</hi> yea, they brought their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and whole Families to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive his bleſſing, and to be
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:51903:55"/> confirmed by him. Which act he performed, not in a tumul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary manner, and as we uſe to ſay, <hi>hand over head,</hi> but with adviſed deliberation and choice, admitting onely thoſe, whom either by the Certificate of their Miniſter, or the exami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of his own Chaplains he found to be ſufficiently inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted in the Principles of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and ſo by the intention of our Church capable of the benefit of that ſacred Action.</p>
               <p n="14">14 In the Cathedral Church of <hi>VVells,</hi> whether it were ſo that himſelf preacht or no, after the Sermon done and the Pſalme ſung as the manner is, Himſelf ſtanding up in the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopal Seat gave the Benedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to the people, after the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:51903:55"/> example of the High Prieſt in the old Teſtament, <hi>Num.</hi> 6. 23. which thing as he performed like himſelf. i. e. In a moſt grave and fatherlike manner; So any man that had but ſeen, with what attentive and devout ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtures all the people received it, what apparent comfort they took in it, and how carefull e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very particular man was, not to depart the Church without it, could not but conclude, That there is a ſecret Virtue in the prayers and bleſſings, as of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural, So of Spiritual Parents.</p>
               <p n="15">15. In his laſt Teſtament, amongſt other pious recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendations of his ſoul to God, he hath theſe words: <hi>I deſire to end my life in that faith, which is now establiſhed in the
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:51903:56"/> Church of England, whereof I am a member, and have been by Gods bleſsing well nigh thirty years a Preacher. And my Souls unfeined deſire is, that it may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver flouriſh, and fructifie in this kingdome and in all his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Dominions, and from thence be propagated to other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, which ſit in darkneſſe and in the ſhadow of death, whether Infidels or Hereticks. Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. Having ſome few hours before his departure made a zealous and devout Confeſſion both of his faith and ſins to the Biſhop of <hi>Ely</hi> there preſent, from whom alſo he received Abſolution, according to the Order of our Church; and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſſiſted to the laſt gaſp with the comfortable and heavenly
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:51903:56"/> prayers of that divine Prelate; after he had taken particular leave of all about him, and gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them reſpectively both his counſel and benediction, He ſpeedily yielded up his ſoul to God.</p>
               <q>Libenter mortalis ſum, qui ſum futurus immortalis.</q>
               <byline>Out of his Preface to his Sermons.</byline>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="biographies">
            <pb n="102" facs="tcp:51903:57"/>
            <head>The ſecond <hi>Decad.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="biography">
               <head>I. EDWARD PEYTO <hi>Eſq;</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. HE was a perſon, who liv'd a great deal of life in a little time; eſpecially dating it (as he did) from the memorable pains of his renovation. When I conſider him in his child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood at the Vniverſity of <hi>Oxf.</hi> exciting others by his example, to minde the end of their being there; how ſtrict and ſtudious he appeared throughout his courſe; how much farther he went before, in point of profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciency,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:51903:57"/> then he came behind others in point of years; how much applauded he was by all, for his publick exerciſes in <hi>Lent,</hi> both as an oratour at the Desk, and as a Philoſopher in the Schools; adding honour to his Degrees. When I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flect upon his progreſs through much variety of learning, through every part of the <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thematicks,</hi> eſpecially through <hi>Algebra</hi> the moſt untroden part of them: and when I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare with all this, the great So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>briety of his temper, his unaffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted humility, and (after a pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick aberration) his perfect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn into the way, out of which for ſome years he had unhappi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly been ſeduced; laſt of all, when I remember, how whileſt
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:51903:58"/> nothing but proſperity made ſome in the world to hug their errour, he hated his ſo much the more, the more he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper'd by its deluſion (which was an argument of the moſt generous and Chriſtian tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per:) I may fitly affirm of him, <hi>That being made perfect in a ſhort time, he fulfilled a long time.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. I do the rather think it a duty, to praiſe him after his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſe, the leſs he was able to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure it, whileſt yet alive. And I conceive my ſelf the fitter, to ſpeak a little in his abse<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of his perfections, becauſe ſo long as he was preſent I onely told him of his faults (never leaving him as a Monitor, untill I thought he left them.) For having
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:51903:58"/> found him my noble friend, I could not but afford him my reprehenſions (yet ſtill attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with reſpect) in whatſoever regard I could think them uſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful. And 'twas the mark of an excellent judicious Spirit, that he valued me moſt for my greateſt freedome in that parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular, even then when our Heads were moſt at enmity (by their over great influence of his Fathers perſwaſion up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his own) there ſtill remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in both our Hearts a moſt inviolable Friendſhip. He had impartially conſidered that ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Aphoriſm, <hi>That to refuſe inſtructions, is to deſpiſe ones own Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. The manner of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture did moſt remarkably
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:51903:59"/> reſemble Sir <hi>Spencer Compton's</hi> (a perſon ſo ſingularly qualifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by grace and nature and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation, that however his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traction was highly noble, I may confidently ſay, it was the loweſt thing in him:) who dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at <hi>Bruges</hi> about the time, wherein the man of our deſires expir'd at <hi>Compton.</hi> Never did I hear of a more heavenly Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lediction to all the content<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. of the earth, then was given by theſe two at their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutions. Never yet did I hear of any two farewells ſo much alike. Never were any more admired by thoſe that ſaw them whileſt they were going, or more deſired when they were gone.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As he deſerves a noble
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:51903:59"/> Elegy, ſo he needs none at all: being one of whom I have ſeldome or never heard an ill word ſpoken. And he was ſo much the leſſe obnoxious to the diſhoneſty of the tongue, becauſe (as far as his Quality would give him leave) he ever delighted in that obſcurity, which moſt young Gentlemen are wont to ſhun. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though his extraction was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and his Fortune extreamly fair; though his natural parts and abilities were truly great, as well as greatly improved by art and induſtry; yet ſtill his modeſty and his meekneſſe were ſo much greater then all the reſt, that, in a perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trariety to the vain glorious and hypocritical, he ever turn'd
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:51903:60"/> his worſt ſide outward.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It was, no doubt, an ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of thoſe two Virtues (his Modeſty and his meekneſſe) that he ſo conſtantly obſerved that precept of S. <hi>Iames:</hi> For he, if any man living, was <hi>ſwift to hear, but ſlow to ſpeak.</hi> And when he thought it his turn to ſpeak, it was rather much, then in many words. As the ſpeech of <hi>Menelaus</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcrib'd by <hi>Homer:</hi> ſo perfectly free were his Diſcourſes, from the fault of impertinencie or ſuperfluity.</p>
               <p n="6">6. So far was he from ſitting down in the chair of the ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full (as too many of his Quality are wont to do:) nay ſo far from walking in the Counſels of the ungodly (from the time that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:51903:60"/> he found them to be ſuch) that he made it his care and chiefeſt caution (in his later years more eſpecially) not ſo much as to ſtand in the way of ſinners.</p>
               <p n="7">7 He was a true Nathaniel, <hi>an Iſraelite indeed,</hi> in whom was <hi>no guile:</hi> a right honeſt man, which is a nobler title then <hi>right honourable;</hi> though I may ſay very truly, that he had many due titles of honour too. For not to ſpeak of his Ance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtors, who came in hither with the Conqueſt, and that from the City <hi>Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ton</hi> in France, from whence they derive the name of <hi>Peyto:</hi> I think it more for his honour, to have been many wayes <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> good: viz. a good Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, and a good Father; a
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:51903:61"/> a good Maſter, and a good Friend; a good Neighbour, and a good Landlord; a good Chriſtian, and a good Man. And, which is a ſign of more goodneſſe then all the reſt, he never thought he was good enough; eſpecially in the firſt, and in the two laſt Particulars.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He was ſo eminently <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> that I believe he was never known to have ſin'd againſt his own body in any kind; ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently <hi>righteous,</hi> that he was in pain, till he had rendered to every man his due. Being ſo ſober, and ſo righteous, he is inferred to have been <hi>Godly</hi> too. For the moſt material part of Godlineſſe is moral ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty; nor was there any thing more conſpicuous in the life
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:51903:61"/> of our bleſſed Lord. The ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Table is the touchſtone of our Obedience to the firſt.</p>
               <p>2. He enjoyed that <hi>Eutha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſia,</hi> that happy calmneſſe of death, which the Emperour <hi>Augustus</hi> was wont to pray for: and that in both accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of the word. For firſt, however he was ſick of a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Fever, yet without the leaſt taint of deliration. That knot of union betwixt his body and his ſoul, was not violently bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken, but very leiſurely untyed; they having parted like two friends, not by a rude falling out, but a loving Farewell. And ſecondly, whereas two things make death terrible, ſudde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>neſs and ſin,: he was ſo armed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the firſt, that he did not
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:51903:62"/> onely take care for the ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of his houſe in order, but ſent for the Divine to aſſiſt his devotion, and farther told his Phyſitian, <hi>that God had ſent him his Summons.</hi> And he uſed the help alſo of our Englisſh Leta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which prompts us to pray <hi>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuddain death,</hi> which he commanded one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to aſſiſt him with upon his death bed, beſtowing upon it (when he had done) a great deal of holy admiration.</p>
               <p n="10">10. Again, ſo well was he prepared againſt the ſecond, that for the tenderneſſe of his Conſcience and his deep re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment of all his ſins, thoſe of the times more eſpecially, in which he deplored his unhap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe that he had had a ſhare:
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:51903:62"/> next for his hatred of himſelf in the remembrance of them, and his ſtedfaſt reſolutions of better life, and of making am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple ſatisfaction for every ill that he had done: and laſt of all for his ſollicitude, that all his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily might live in the fear of God: in all theſe reſpects, I ſay, he appears a more then ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Example.</p>
               <p n="11">11. Marks of his <hi>ſincerity</hi> were: 1. That he lookt upon his failings, as through a <hi>macroſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cope,</hi> which made them ſeem nearer and very much greater then they were. 'Twas his own expreſſion, <hi>That all the ſins of his former life did even kick in his very face;</hi> warning all thoſe who ſtood about his ſick bed, to beware of thoſe ſins which
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:51903:63"/> the world cals <hi>little;</hi> and of the <hi>no-little</hi> ſins, which the world calls none; yea of the leaſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearances and opportunities of ſin 2. That he was not meerly a <hi>death bed penitent,</hi> but began the great work in his time of health. 3. That he inſiſted on the nature of true repentance, w<hi rend="sup">ch</hi> ſtill importeth an amend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and reformation of life: abhorring and deploring thoſe deſperate notions of repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which the world is ſo co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly miſtaken in. 4. That after ſome <hi>Conflicts</hi> he had with the Ghoſtly enemy (that ſo he might be happier in a Victori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, then he could poſſibly have been in an untempted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocence) God was pleas'd ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſignally to ſpeak peace unto
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:51903:63"/> his Conſcience, and to give him a foretaſt of Glory. 5. That he extended his care to the ſouls of others, with as true a Charity as to his own; exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one againſt the love of this world, charging another to be watchfull againſt intem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perance, exciting a third un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to frequent and ſervent pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er. In general and in ſpecial, he was by his precepts as well as practice, a true preacher of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In imitation of good old <hi>Iacob,</hi> before he was ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered to his Fathers, he gave a bleſſing to all his Children. And farther gave it in charge to his virtuous Conſort, not to edu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate his Children, ſo much to learning and other accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:51903:64"/> as to the knowledge and ſervice and fear of God: and that they ſhould be ſeaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with thoſe his laſt principles, which by his later experience he found the beſt.</p>
               <p>Ob. 8. Cal. 7. An. 1658. aet 31.</p>
               <byline>Out of his Funeral Sermon by Mr. Thomas Peirce.</byline>
            </div>
            <div type="biography">
               <head>Dr. WILLIAM LAUD, <hi>Arch.</hi> B. of <hi>Canterbury</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. HE was by many ſuſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted and charged not onely as popiſhly affected him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but as a poiſoner of the whole ſtream and current of the reformed religion in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland:</hi> at laſt he was treated ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a <hi>heretick</hi> or a <hi>traitor,</hi> or both, to Church and State.</p>
               <p n="2">
                  <pb n="117" facs="tcp:51903:64"/>2. As to this aſperſion of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eing popiſh in his judgment (which reflected, in the repute and event, upon all the Biſhops of <hi>England</hi>) truly his own Book may beſt of any, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently vindicate him to be a great <hi>Antipapist:</hi> great I ſay; becauſe it ſeems by that learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſpute, that he diſſented from Popery, not upon popu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Surmiſes and eaſie Prejudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, but very learned and ſolid grounds, which true reaſon and religion make good, agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the judgement of the Catholick Church in the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and beſt times. And in this the Aarch B. doth to my judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo very impartially weigh the ſtate and weight of all the conſiderable differences be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:51903:65"/> the Papiſts and the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh</hi> Proteſtants (not ſuch as are ſimple, futile and fanatick, but learned, ſerious and ſober) that he neither gratifies the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maniſt</hi> nor exaſperates him be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond what is juſt; neither warp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a novel and needleſſe ſuper-reformation, wich is a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity on the right hand, nor to a ſub-reformation which is a deformity on the left; but keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that golden mean, which was held by the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> and the greateſt defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of it.</p>
               <p n="3">3. I am indeed prone to think, that he wiſhed there could have been any fair cloſe or accommodation between all Chriſtian Churches (the ſame which many grave and
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:51903:65"/> earned men have much deſir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:) And it may be, he thought himſelf no unfit Inſtrument to make way for ſo great and good a work, conſidering the eminencies of parts, power and favour which he had. Haply he judged (as many learned and moderate men have) that in ſome things be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween Papiſts and Proteſtants, differences are made wider, &amp; kept more open, raw and ſore then need be, by the private pens and paſſions of ſome men, and the intereſts of ſome little parti's, whoſe partial policies re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally neglect the publick &amp; true intereſt of the Catholick Church and Chriſtian religion, which conſiſts much in peace as well as in purity, in Charity as in U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:51903:66"/>4. He was neither <hi>Calviniſt,</hi> nor <hi>Lutheran,</hi> nor <hi>Papiſt,</hi> as to any ſide or party, but all, ſo far as he ſaw they agreed with the reformed Church of <hi>England,</hi> either in fundamentals, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and decent ſuperſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures. Nor did he eſteem any thing as the Voice of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which was not publickly agreed to and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared by King and Parliament, according to the advice and determinate judgement of a National Synod and lawfull Convocation convened and approved by the chief Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, which together made up the compleat Repreſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, the full ſenſe and ſuffrage of this Church.</p>
               <p n="5">5. After his confinement,
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:51903:66"/> having occaſion to wait on him, <hi>I heard him</hi> proteſting with a ſerious atteſtation of his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ntegrity before Gods omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, that however he might miſtake in the mean and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod, yet he never had any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther deſign then the glory of God, the ſervice of his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, and the good order peace and deconcy of the Church of <hi>England:</hi> that he was ſo far from complying with Papiſts, in order to confirm them in their errours, that he rather choſe ſuch methods to advance the honour of the Reformed Religion in <hi>England,</hi> as he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved might ſooneſt ſilence the cavils of fiercer Papiſts, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce the more moderate Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſants to come in to us, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:51903:67"/> leſſe viſible occaſion gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them by needleſſe diſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and diſputes to ſeparate from us.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He added, that he had (further) a deſire, as much as he could, to relieve the poor and diſtreſſed condition of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Miniſters, whom he had to his grief obſerved in <hi>Wales</hi> and <hi>England,</hi> where their diſcou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragements were very great by reaſon of the tenuity and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>competency of their Livings: That he found the ſordid and ſhamefull aſpect of religion, and the Clergy gave great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages to thoſe that were Popiſhly inclined, who would hardly ever think it beſt for them to joyn with that Church, which did not maintain either
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:51903:67"/> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ts own honour or its Clergy to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ome competency and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ineſſe.</p>
               <p n="7">7. Doubtleſſe this Prelate <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad more in him of Charity, Liberality, Munificence and Magnificence (as appears by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he works he undertook to found, to build or to repair) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hen ever I ſaw in any of thoſe, who are the <hi>having</hi> and <hi>get<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing</hi> from, not the giving ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to, <hi>Epiſcopacy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="additions">
               <head>Aditions of <hi>ARCH-BISHOP LAUD.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. HE was born of honeſt Parents at <hi>Reading</hi> in <hi>Barkſhire.</hi> There he built an <hi>Almes-houſe</hi> and endowed it
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:51903:68"/> with 200 <hi>l. per an.</hi> As appears by his own Diary, which he conſtantly kept of all the paſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of his life.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He was very plain in ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, and ſharply checkt ſuch Clergy-men whom he ſaw go in rich or gaudy clothes, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly calling them of the Church triumphant. At a Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation in <hi>Eſſex</hi> reproving a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter for his fineneſſe, &amp; ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his own plaine apparel, he received this anſwer: <hi>My Lord, You have better clothes at home, and I have worſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. His munificence appears chiefly by St. <hi>Iohns</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford</hi> (where he was bred) beautified, enlarged and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched by him: and by St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Church, the Maſter-piece of
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:51903:68"/> his deſignes. One Satyrically ſaid, <hi>He pluckt down Puritans &amp; Property, to build up Pauls &amp; Prerogative.</hi> But now that Church, formerly approacht with due reverence, is entred with fear of the falling of it: and is ſo far from having its old decayes repaired, that it is dai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly decayed in its new repara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
               <p n="4">4. An. 1645. <hi>Ian.</hi> 10. He was brought to the Scaffold, which he aſcended with a chearfull Countenance, as ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to gain a Crown then loſe a head: He made a Sermon-Speech on Heb. 12. <hi>Let us run with patience &amp;c.</hi> Proteſted his innocence and integrity, as never intending any ſubver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of Laws and Liberty; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:51903:69"/> his inward comfort; had his head ſtricken off at one blow, while he prayed, <hi>Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> receive my Soul.</hi>
               </p>
               <byline>Out of <hi>Dr. Gaudens</hi> Eccleſiae Ang. Suſpiria, B. 4. ch. 23.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="biography">
               <head>III. ARCH-BISHOP USHER.</head>
               <p n="1">1. Dr. <hi>Iames Vſher,</hi> lat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Arch-biſhop of <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh</hi> and Lord Primate of <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> I reckon as ours, becauſe not onely his aſhes and morta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> remains are depoſited with us, but he lived his laſt years o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Exile, and ended his mortality amongſt us in <hi>England.</hi> Wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> beſides his conſtant pains i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> preaching, even to his laſt, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:51903:69"/> hath left as many of his learned works, which are enjoyed by, and highly eſteemed of all worthy men, who were bleſt with the example of his great and unſpotted worth, which no envy, no malice can, I think, be ſo impudent as to blemiſh.</p>
               <p n="2">2. The real excellencies of this Biſhop every way were ſuch, that they exceeded all or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary meaſures of humane commendation and capacity, extending to ſomething of ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miration <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </note> and ecſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. None but thoſe whoſe minds are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larged to ſome proportion of his accompliſhments can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to comprehend his worth and amplitude: So vaſt, ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent, ſo aſtoniſhing was his
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:51903:70"/> learning and underſtanding in all kinds of knowledge, divine and humane, that he was as the <hi>Cynoſure</hi> by which all great Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines ſteered, and as the Sun-Dial by which all great Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars ſet their watches.</p>
               <p n="3">3. So accurate was he in all uſefull and learned Languages, occidental and oriental; So clear a proſpect he had of all Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory and Chronology, of all Controverſies, antient and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern, that nothing eſcaped him: nor was he onely as a Reader and ſpectatour, but as a Judge and Cenſor, as an Arbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trator and Dictator in Diſputes, as one that ſate in a Tribunal of Soveraign Learning over all. Nothing was new or hid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to him in Philology, Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy,
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:51903:70"/> Geography, Aſtrono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, Mathematicks, and leaſt of all in Theology or Divinity: he had conquered all others, but in this he triumphed, which was the Trophie, Crown and Centor of all his other ſtudies.</p>
               <p n="4">4. There was ſcarce any Book, printed or manuſcript, worth reading, in private or publick Libraries throughout all Chriſtendome, which he had not read, either in the Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py or Original, and digeſted in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the method or deſign of his ſtudies; yea, and to a miracle remembred, as to the main contents of it. To the immen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity of his learning there was ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded excellent Principles of Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick Prudence, as a Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of the Church, and as a
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:51903:71"/> Counſellour of State, taken from that great experience he had gotten, and many excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Obſervations he had made out of all Hiſtories, as well hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane as divine; though he al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways laid the greateſt weight upon the grounds and inſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of holy Scripture, which gives the trueſt judgement of Wiſdome or Folly.</p>
               <p n="5">5. His whole life, as to the Converſable part of it, was ſo civil, ſo ſacred, ſo affable, ſo am<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ble to all perſons of any worth or ingenuity that came to him, that nothing was more Venerable. I never ſaw him either moroſe or reſerved, much leſſe ſower or ſupercili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous. If he were ſad, it made him not ſilent, but onely more
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:51903:71"/> ſolemn: if he were chearfull, he abhorred not ſuch facetious and ingenious elegancies of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, as ſhewed that holineſs was no enemy to Cheerfulneſs, but great Graces might ſafely ſmile, and innocent Virtues might ſometimes laugh with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out offence.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Whoſe humble and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Induſtry was ſuch, that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides his vaſt deſignes for wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and printing, he never fail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſince he was Presbyter, Prelate or Primate, to preach once every week, if health per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted him; beſides many times on the week dayes upon occaſion: Nor was it any great pains to a perſon of his fulneſſe, who did not pump for, but pour out his Sermons like a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:51903:72"/> pregnant ſpring, with a ſtrange plenty, clarity and vivacity. If all Biſhops hearts and mouthes had been as open as his, ſure they had ſtopped the mouthes and ſilenced the tongues of all their Adverſaries.</p>
               <p n="7">7. However, He held a fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Correſpondency and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctual Communion (as occaſion offered) with thoſe Reformed Churches, and thoſe Miniſters, who approved, yea deſired E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcopacy, though they could not enjoy any Biſhops, properly ſo called, after the cuſtome of all antient Churches; yet, with S. <hi>Cyprian</hi> 
                  <note n="::" place="margin">Sine ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ſunt, &amp; perditio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem maximam Dei indignati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one acquirunt, qui ſchi ſmata ſerunt, &amp; relicto Epiſcopo ſuo, ultro ſibi foras pſeudo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcopum conſtituunt. Epiſt. 61. Lib 1.</note> he flatly condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and branded
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:51903:72"/> with the ſin and ſcandal of Schiſm, all thoſe who wilfully caſt off, injuſtly ſeparated from their lawfull Biſhops, who pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed the ſame Orthodox Faith and reformed Religion; affirming that he would not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the Sacrament at ſuch Miniſters hands.</p>
               <p n="8">8. This excellent Biſhop, who deſerved to be eſteemed one of the Primates of all Lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, Piety and Virtue in the Chriſtian world, was, by Gods wonderfull diſpenſations, made a Primate in ſufferings. He li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to ſee, yea to feel, his Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Perſon by ſome men ſhamefully ſlighted, his Fun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction as a Biſhop exautorated, decryed, depreſſed, diſpiſed; his Revenues firſt ſtopped, then
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:51903:73"/> alienated and confiſcated; his moderate ſtock of moveables (all, except his excellent Libra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry) and at laſt a reſerve of ſome moneys, ſeized and ſwept away by the <hi>Iriſh.</hi> After this, the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits of the Biſhoprick of <hi>Carlile</hi> (then vacant) being conferred on him by the late King, for the ſupport of his age and exile, even theſe were taken from him by thoſe that took all Church-revenues from all Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops: and a Penſion allowed him, which, after a year or two, was never paid him.</p>
               <p n="9">9. At laſt this great Perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage, the Primate of <hi>Armagh</hi> (whom Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> with many other great Princes and States, had invited with very honorary Propoſitions to
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:51903:73"/> make onely his reſidence with them, as an honour to their Countrey) was reduced to a ſmal Stipend or Salary, which he was to earn by preaching, as long as his ſight and ſtrength ſerved him. Theſe failing him (&amp; in him all the learned &amp; bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter world) he lived upon Gods providence and the Contribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions (for the moſt part) of ſome noble Perſonages (where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in I was happy to do him ſome ſervice:) among whom none hath merited and erected a more laſting Monument of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour, then the Counteſſe of <hi>Peterborough;</hi> under whoſe gratefull and hoſpitable roof this mortal Angel, this incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parable Biſhop left, as the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> ſo all the world, which was not worthy of him.</p>
               <pb n="136" facs="tcp:51903:74"/>
               <byline>Out of <hi>Dr. Gaudens</hi> Eccleſ. Ang. S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pipria B. 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h. 24.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="biography">
               <head>IV. THOMAS BRANDESTON</head>
               <p n="1">1. A Rich Clothier of <hi>Berg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holt</hi> (commonly, <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold</hi>) in <hi>Suffolk,</hi> and more rich in good works, for which his Memory is freſh, and will ever be preſerved there. Whoſe example is worthy to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to all the Clothiers in <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. He well knew, that thrift and diligence muſt bring in fewell for munificence: and was both himſelf a laborious man in his Calling, and an exact Overſeer of his Workfolks,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:51903:74"/> not enduring idleneſſe, no nor any vain expences.</p>
               <p n="3">3. His manner was, as he walked along the ſtreet to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the painfulneſſe of the poorer ſort, and at the Houſes where he heard them diligent at their buſineſs, to caſt in at the doors his money liberally, and ſo knockt and away. Which cuſtome of his the people were ſo acquainted with, that they knew his knock, and would haſten to the door and gladly take up his Almes.</p>
               <p n="4">4. Often did he viſit the poor Houſes, and look into their Cupboards, and finding but ſlender proviſion there, leave money with them to buy them bread: and if he percei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved them to want Clothes,
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:51903:75"/> took care they ſhould be better apparelled at his charge.</p>
               <p n="5">5. It was his Cuſtome alſo to provide many Sutes of ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel, and give them to ſome friend or ſervant to be diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. Go, ſaid he, and diſpoſe of theſe Commodities, and that they may go off the better, take mony with you, and give ſo much to one, and ſo much to another, that they may ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept of the Clothes the more willingly. Sometimes he would ſend for the Taylors and cauſe them to cut out apparel for the poor out of a whole broad Cloth. For ſuch Clothiers the Lord provides bright ſhining Robes of Glory in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p n="6">6. He uſed to go to the week<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:51903:75"/> Lecture at <hi>Manigtree,</hi> &amp; there had two purſes full of money: the one he would empty to the poor that came there to his chamber; the other to others that would wait for him on the way as he returned home. This was his way to lay up his Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in heaven, where no theeves can break through and ſteal.</p>
               <p n="7">7. At <hi>Barfold</hi> on the Lecture day the Miniſters that met at Church were conſtantly enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained at his houſe and feaſted, being pleaſed no leſſe with his company and good diſcourſe then with his good chear: And in another fair room were fed at the ſame time a good num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of poor people, that were his welcome gueſts at all times.</p>
               <p n="8">8. He would ſometimes de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:51903:76"/> himſelf in a relation, how his liberality once ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him a thouſand pounds. For, coming from <hi>London</hi> with this great charge of money, and alone, he was ſet on by rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and diſtributing among them readily at the firſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand four or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive pounds, they were ſo taken with his chearfull Bounty, that they did not ſearch him, but guarded him on his way homeward till he was paſt danger of the reſt of their Confederates; for which civility he freely gave them forty ſhillings more.</p>
               <p n="9">9. This good man had one ſore affliction in his eldeſt Daughter, troubled ſome ſpace of time with a great Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, believing God would
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:51903:76"/> damn her: with whom after he had uſed all fair means to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceive her and adminiſter comfort (but in vain) he took this courſe. He calls her into his private chamber, and with a ſtern countenance ſaid thus. Thou thinkeſt God has no mercy for thee, but will ſurely damn thee: come on then, and blaſpheem that God. The daughter was amazed at this command of her Father, and when he ſtill preſſed it (to try her) fell down at his feet and cryed out: Though you be my Father, yet I dare not at your command ſin againſt my God: I dare not blaſpheem his holy name. Thou fool, ſaid the Father, with tears in his eyes: and canſt thou think, that that
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:51903:77"/> God whom thou feareſt to diſpleaſe, whom thou dareſt not ſin againſt, can be ſo cruel as to damn thee. Avoid Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan, The poor Daughter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived comfort preſently, and the good Father was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed.</p>
               <p n="10">10. To leave the reſt to the remembrance of thoſe that knew him, I adde but one thing more. Every Lords day after morning Sermon, he retired to his chamber and ſpent his Dinner-time in Meditation: but, at Supper, he feaſted his Family, and his Children, that were placed out and married in the Town; and thus did both receive much joy himſelf, and maintained unity, and amity amongſt them. Farewell, brave
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:51903:77"/> Clothier! May thy Example <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ever be forgoten.</p>
               <byline>From Tradition of good hands.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="biography">
               <head>IV. Mr. JOHN DOD.</head>
               <p>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. HE was born at <hi>Shotledge</hi> in <hi>Cheſhire,</hi> (the young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of ſeventeen children) bred <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n <hi>Ieſus</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge.</hi> At a Diſputation at one Commencement, he was ſo facetiouſly ſolid, that <hi>Oxford</hi>-men there preſent courted him home with them, and would have planted him in their Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity.</p>
               <p>2. He was a paſſive <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſt,</hi> not loving any one the worſe for difference in judgement about Ceremonies, and acknowledged how God
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:51903:78"/> under the government of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops had given a marvelous encreaſe to the Goſpel, and that godly men might Compo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> therewith comfortably. And to his dying day is conceived (though roughly uſed) to have ſtuck to what he had written on the five Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mentaries of O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience to lawfull Authority.</p>
               <p>3. Some Gallants at Sr. <hi>A. Cope's</hi> Table forbore ſwearing in reverence of Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> being preſent: and confeſſing ſo much, he took occaſion thence to diſcourſe of the power of Gods reſtraining grace: and how it would keep us from wickedneſs, were we not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to our ſelves.</p>
               <p>4. He would ſit along while in contemplation of a flower,
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:51903:78"/> &amp; ſaid to one inviting him to ſee a fair houſe, I can ſee much of God, even in this little flower: more then in your ſtately build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings.</p>
               <p>5. When the Souldiers had plundered him of his linnen, he in their abſence to ſearch af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more, took a pair of the ſheets, and clapt them under him in his chair, and ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceals them and ſaves them from the Souldiers, much pleaſing himſelf after their departure, that he had, as he ſaid, <hi>plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered the plunderers,</hi> and by a lawfull felony ſaved ſomewhat of his goods.</p>
               <p>6. He was an exquiſite He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brician, and with his ſociety and directions in one Vacation taught that tongue to Mr. <hi>Iohn
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:51903:79"/> Gregory</hi> that rare linguiſt, Chaplain of Chriſt Church, who ſurvived him but one year, dying at <hi>Kidlington Mar.</hi> 13. 1646. buried at Chriſt-Church in <hi>Oxford.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>7. Mr. <hi>Dod</hi> dyed 1645. &amp; was buried at <hi>Fauſly</hi> in <hi>Northam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pton-ſhire:</hi> with whom the old Puritan may ſeem to expire, and in his grave to be interr'd. Humble, Meek, Patient, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpital, Charitable, as in his Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of, ſo in his almes to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, would I could truly ſay but half ſo much of the next Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration.</p>
               <byline>Out of <hi>Mr. Fullers</hi> Church-Hiſtory.</byline>
            </div>
            <div type="biography">
               <pb n="147" facs="tcp:51903:79"/>
               <head>Mr. JOSEPH MEDE</head>
               <p n="1">1. HIs parents were of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt rank, and though not by eminency of Condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ion, yet truly ennobled by hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng ſuch a Son: of whom alſo <hi>Eſſex</hi> (near <hi>Biſhops Stratford</hi>) may juſtly glory as the place of his Nativity.</p>
               <p n="2">2. His friends, encouraged by their conceived hopes of him in his bloſſome, plac'd him in the Univerſity of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> devoting him to learning in the ſervice of Chriſt, in that Coll. that bears his name. And what pains himſelf took for his own improvement, may eaſily be imagined; and that to the rich vein of his pregnant wit, an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiduous
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:51903:80"/> induſtry was not want<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The fruits whereof, ſoon appeared with that luſtre, that drew upon him the eyes not onely of thoſe in his own Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, but of the whole Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity: who lookt upon him, as one eminent in all kind of learning requiſite for his ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He wanted that felicity of utterance, which uſes to ſet off a ſleight knowledge, having ſo great an heſitation in his ſpeech, as made his expreſſions painful to himſelf, and nothing pleaſing to others. wherein yet, he in time became a rare ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, how much a diſcreet obſervation of ſuch an imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection can work toward the cure of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. For by a heedfull
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:51903:80"/> inſpection into the nature of his defect, what words he moſt ſtuck at, either ſingle, or in Conjuncture, and at what times he was more or leſſe freo; he attained ſo great a maſtery over that infirmity, that he was able to deliver a whole Sermon without any conſiderable he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitation.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By that time he had ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken the degree of a Maſter in Arts, he had made ſo happy a progreſſe through all kind of Academical ſtudies, as that Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle was not (as with many it is) any falſe inſcription. His name was up, and he lookt on as one extraordinary ſeen in all thoſe Arts and Languages that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſh a Divine: an acute Logician, a profound Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher,
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:51903:81"/> a skilful Mathematician, and one not ſlightly verſed in Hiſtory and Chronology. In all which, but eſpecially in theſe laſt ſtudies, he after became ſo great a Proſicient, that for his ſingular knowledge and dex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous application of Propheſie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to their punctual times, he was worthily admir'd by thoſe tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knew him.</p>
               <p n="5">5. His firſt ſhewing himſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> abroad was by an addreſſe to that great pattern and Patron o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> learning, <hi>Andrews</hi> (after Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop of <hi>Wincheſter</hi>) in a large diſcourſe in Latine <hi>de Sanctuat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> relativa.</hi> Which gained the approbation of ſo exact a judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment (as was his to whom i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> was preſented) in ſo high a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> meaſure, that the Biſhop ſtood
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:51903:81"/> his firm friend in a buſineſſe at Court about his fellowſhip, and after that deſired him for his houſhold Chaplain: which place, notwithſtanding he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed, as valuing the freedome of his ſtudies above any hopes of preferment. And this free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome which he enjoyed in his Cell (as he uſed chearfully to term it) gave him a happy advantage of encreaſing his knowledge in all kinds.</p>
               <p n="6">6. His conſtant reading the Greek Lecture in the Colledge (which he obtained ſoon after his being choſen Fellow, and held all his life) made that tongue familiar to him: and his daily private readings to his pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils (to whom he was an able guide in all kind of Philoſophi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:51903:82"/> and Mathematical ſtudies) preſerved theſe parts of Acade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mical learning. Nor were his hours of recreation (which was very ſeldome in bodily exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) this way unprofitable to himſelf and others, being for the moſt part ſpent in learned diſcourſes with his friends; and for divers years together moſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what with his worthy friend Mr. <hi>William Chappell,</hi> Hebrew Lecturer, in the ſame Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, keeping that language in continual exerciſe; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, by many happy excurſions into the neighbouring Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages, gained no ſmall trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of knowledge in the <hi>Chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dee, Syriac,</hi> and <hi>Arabic.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. The time he had for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirement to his private ſtudies,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:51903:82"/> he ſpent principally in a curi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous enquiring into the more abſtruſe parts of learning, and ſuch as were remote from the vulgar track. As in the exact calculation of time for clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the hiſtorical part of Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture: to which he joyned the laborious ſearch of Antiquities relating to Religion, Ethnick, Jewiſh and Chriſtian. The fruits of which ſtudy appear vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible in his works.</p>
               <p n="8">8. Among other ſtudies he ſpent no ſmall pains in ſound<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the depths of Aſtrology: and was wont in familiar diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to determine, that (to uſe his own appoſite and fit words) the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>coeli</hi> does be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get in man <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>temperamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> and this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>temperamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ti</hi>
                  <pb n="154" facs="tcp:51903:83"/> does beget <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nii,</hi> in the way of direct and natural ſubordination: but, that here the chain is broken off, becauſe <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ingen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i</hi> does beget or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>actionis</hi> in man only contingently, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any neceſſity. And thus <hi>è contra,</hi> that <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>coel:</hi> does beget <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>temperamenti,</hi> and the <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>temperamenti,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>ingen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> this naturally, as before: But, that this <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>i</hi> ſhould beget <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>actio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis,</hi> this is from no neceſſity; becauſe it is in mans power and liberty, who is naturally ill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſpoſed, through the improve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of art, and eſpecially by the grace of God, to become good or better, as the divine goodneſſe ſhall miniſter oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity.
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:51903:83"/> Which is as much as can be ſaid in ſo few words, and might determine the queſtion to all judicious and knowing men, concerning the power of the ſtarrs and thoſe celeſtial in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluences.</p>
               <p n="9">9. From theſe he proceeded unto thoſe myſterious Scien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which made the ancient Chaldeans and Egyptians ſo fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, tracing them, as far as he could have any light to guide him, in their Prophetick Schemes, Hieroglyphicks, and Oneiromancy, or interpreta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of dreams, for the affinity which he conceived they might have with the language of the Prophets: to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of which he ſhewed a moſt indefatigable deſire: as
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:51903:84"/> witneſs eſpecially thoſe labours of his which are publiſhed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. He ever ſeemed moſt delighted with thoſe ſtudies, where he might ſtrain the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>news of his brain: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore uſed to ſet upon thoſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficult places of Scripture, where he found errour had inſconced it ſelf with obſcurity, antiquity or multitude of miſtakes. By this means he became furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with variety of diſcourſe, of things no leſſe delightfull and profitable, then out of the vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar rode of ſtudies. Which made his company much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired and frequented by Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, both of the ſame Colledge and from abroad. To theſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e ſeemed to impart himſelf
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:51903:84"/> with that willingneſſe, that it ſeemed queſtionable, whether had the greater deſire, they to hear, or he to communicate his ſtudies to them. Which made a familiar friend of his once mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily to ſay to ſome, that, having been partakers of his diſcourſes, gave him thanks: <hi>That they might ſpare their thanks; for that they were not ſo much beholding to him for delivering himſelf to them, as he was to them for hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. By this means he ſo fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his notions in his memory, that he made them ever his own, and himſelf able at any time readily to deliver them in a compleat and well formed diſcourſe. Such are thoſe ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Diatribae</hi> now publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:51903:85"/> wherein he hath diſcover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed more rarities and pieces of profound and unvulgar learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, then are to be found in ſome vaſt volumes of many much admired Authours. Theſe were Academical exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes calculated for the meridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an of an Univerſity, and not fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for the vulgar.</p>
               <p n="12">12. In popular Diſcourſes or Sermons, he diſliked the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neceſſary quotation of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thours and the uſe of forreign languages and terms of Art (too much practiſed even among men, otherwiſe learned and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious) as ſavouring of as much inconſideration, as for ſhoo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> makers (it was his compariſon) <hi>to bring ſhoos to be drawn on with their laſts in them:</hi> And would
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:51903:85"/> ſay, that Arts and Languages, though they were neceſſary and excellent helps for the framing of any d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſcourſe, &amp; to enable men to inſtruct others, yet were they to be laid by in diſcourſes to the unlearned.</p>
               <p n="13">13. He was ſo far from the vanity of oſtentation, that it is heard to ſay, whether he was more eminent for his rare knowledge, or for his ſingular modeſty in valuing his own a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilities: in ſo much as he could, not without trouble, hear of that opinion, which ſome (de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervedly enough) had conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of his great learning; own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing onely ſome diligence, free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome from prejudice and <hi>ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium partium</hi> as his beſt abili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties. To this, as a near alliance
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:51903:86"/> of modeſty may be added his a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſneſſe from all ambitious thoughts, &amp; affectation of great and publick places, to the pu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuance of which many have been ſpurred by the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of leſſer abilities. It was indeed his higheſt ambition to be <hi>in tranquillitatc &amp; ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſſu.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. His great knowledge did not (as it doth with many) make him apt either to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with any, or for difference in opinion to break the bond of amity: but was ever moſt ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derly ſtudious of the peace of the Church. To whoſe cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure he ever ſubmitted his pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate judgement, being willing either to reform or ſilence any opinion, which ſhould be found repugnant to truth, or
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:51903:86"/> inconſiſtent to peace. He lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved not to entertain diſcourſe with them, that were impetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and paſſionate in their opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, who were reſolved however to have the laſt word, being more addicted to that un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingenious humour (as he was wont to call it) of <hi>Diſputacity,</hi> then a ſober and moderate diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſition after truth. And in that unhappy difference about Predeſtination and its Appen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dants, he would often ſay, that he wondred that men ſhould, with ſo great animoſity, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend about thoſe high and ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure ſpeculations, and with ſo ſevere a confidence condemn each other.</p>
               <p n="15">15. His Humility and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity (rare virtues in this age!)
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:51903:87"/> appeared particularly in theſe three inſtances. 1. That he was never forward (in what company ſoever) to catch at hints of diſcourſe, or to declare his opinion in a way of ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larity: and yet he was the moſt communicative man in the world. 2. That he would fair<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly propound, dextrouſly illu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate, and ingenuouſly leave every man to judge for himſelf, being not ambitious at all to gain Proſelytes, nor magiſterial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly impoſing his notions upon other men, but contented eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one ſhould think or ſpeak as himſelf beſt liked. 3. That he would ſpeak ill of no man; but diſſemble the failings &amp; errours of his very enemies: neither would he willingly accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:51903:87"/> them, who in the pregnan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy or pruriency of wit would adventure to criticize upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, to the diſparagement of their parts or performances.</p>
               <p n="16">16. That the fear of God had a great impreſſion upon his ſoul, he manifeſted, not onely by a religious and innocent Converſation, but in all his diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes: in which, he ever ſhewed himſelf tender of the honour of God, and that he could not brook the leaſt adul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration of his worſhip, nor the violation of any thing upon which his awfull name was ſtamped. Hence was that ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verity which he uſed againſt the Roman Church in their Saint and Image-worſhip. Hence likewiſe was his ſo great deteſtation of Sacriledge, and
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:51903:88"/> ſo zealous aſſerting the honour of Gods houſe, and whatſoever elſe is dedicated to his worſhip, exacting a reverence from Chriſtians in the uſe of them in relation to God, to whom by a peculiar propriety they belong. This latter procured him the ſuſpicion of Superſtition with ſuch as ſhew their zeal againſt idolatry by committing or at leaſt by approving of Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and baniſh all diſtinction between things ſacred and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane, and meaſure the truth of every point of religion by its diſtance from Rome. But his reputation not ſtanding or falling <hi>arbitrio popularis aurae,</hi> it would but wrong him, to go about to vindicate him from ſuch mens cenſure. Neither
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:51903:88"/> need I cleare him from the guilt of Time-ſerving in what he hath written for <hi>Reverence in Gods houſe,</hi> having declared it to be his opinion many years before the times reliſht it.</p>
               <p n="17">17. His ſoul, while it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſed in theſe regions of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, was inveſted in a come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and healthfull body, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what beyond a juſt temper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clined to melancholy; yet ſo, as that melancholy ſeemed ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to poyſe, and make it ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable to his ſtudious minde, then to diſtemper it with thoſe infirmities which commonly attend the predominancy of that humour. His feeding, for the moſt part, was rather to ſuffice nature, then ſatisfie his appetite. No man more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:51903:89"/> to his Colledge-Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, with the ſmaller ſort of beer, ſeldome and very little wine. Which made him of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten merrily to tell them which obſerved the thriving of his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, that <hi>They might ſee what Colledg-Commons could do.</hi> And as his body with ſmall Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, ſo his purſe, with a ſmall <hi>Intrado,</hi> received a conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble improvement.</p>
               <p n="18">18. He was taken away with a ſhort (for it ended the fourth day) and not very pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſickneſſe, his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, judgement and memory continuing in vigour to his laſt gaſp. He bequeathed towards the new building, the increaſe of the Library, the adorning of the Chappel: a large Legacy
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:51903:89"/> out of a Scholars purſe, of 300. <hi>l.</hi> in way of a grateful return for thoſe mercies he had ſo long enjoyed in that Colledge, whereof he was a member.</p>
               <p n="19">19. He compoſed his ſoul (which he then was onely to attend) for its addreſſe into the divine preſence with moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vout thoughts and humble prayers, and ſtrengthned it with the commemoration of his death, by whom he hoped to obtain a more bleſſed life, in the participation of the ſacred Euchariſt. And having thus taken and taſted the cup of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation, within a few hours he departed hence, to the more full fruition of thoſe heavenly delicates, among thoſe bleſſed ones <hi>that are called to the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:51903:90"/> of the Lamb,</hi> upon the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>Octob.</hi> 1638. When he had lived 53 years, and ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove two thirds of that time in that Colledge, to which living he was ſo great an ornament and dead, his worthy name ſhall be a laſting monument. <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>A compleat Edition of all</hi> Mr. Mede's <hi>Works in Fol. is promiſed by</hi> R. R.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="20">20. He had this happineſſe in his death, that he was taken away from the evils that were then ready to come, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Truth and Peace</hi> had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun to ſuffer in this unhappy Iſland. And indeed he would often, in the preſage of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vining ſpirit, ſpeak of this, a year or two before he dyed, as an obſervation upon that in the 3. of <hi>Iudges 30. The land
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:51903:90"/> had reſt four ſcore years:</hi> 
                  <q>which now (would he ſay) that from the begining of bleſſed <hi>Queen Elizabeth's</hi> reign, we of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland</hi> have enjoyed: who knowes whether our period may not be near at hand? And whether it be ſo, or not, whoſoever ſhall live but a year or two may know it of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain.</q>
               </p>
               <byline>Out of the View of his Life annexed to his Works.</byline>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="biography">
               <head>VII. Mr. JOSIAS SHUTE.</head>
               <p>HIs very name is as a ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver Trumpet to his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>utation, ſounding out a <hi>Quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uid doctiorum eſt, aſſurgite
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:51903:91"/> huic tam colendo nomini:</hi> with whom 'twas, as with <hi>Iob</hi> appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, <hi>ch.</hi> 29. The young men hid themſelves, and the aged aroſe and ſtood up: when the ear heard him, then it bleſſed him; and when the eye ſaw him, it gave witneſſe to him. His name, I ſay, is an Aromatick oyntment, diffuſing a more rich perfume then the choiceſt of our broken boxes.</p>
               <p>2. He was deſcended of a Learned Race, the ſon of an eminent Divine in <hi>Yorkſhire,</hi> and one of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive famous brother<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preachers. A man of that lati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude of learning, that length of apprehenſion, that depth of judgement and height of ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culation, ſo compleat in all de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menſions, that I may juſtly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>new
<pb n="171" facs="tcp:51903:91"/> that admiration of <hi>Naz.</hi> concerning <hi>Baſil</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Where was there ſuch a mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of rare parts and graces? what kind of learning was he unacquainted with? what kind was he not excellent in, as if he had ſtudied that alone.</p>
               <p>3. And though he were a man of but a ſingle heart, yet was he one of divers tongues, able to read the Scriptures without the ſpectacles of Tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlatours; he both drank and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived thoſe holy waters out of their ſweeter Fountains, the Originals. And even <hi>Bellar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine</hi> acknowledges, the Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginal is in ſeveral caſes to be u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Melancthon</hi> valued their skill in the Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals above Kingdomes, ſaith
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:51903:92"/> 
                  <hi>Amama in paraen. L. H.</hi> Our grave Authour, like a wiſe Merchant, was well skild in the tongue of the place he traded to: being Maſter of thoſe three grand mother Languages, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed on the Croſſe of Chriſt, beſides ſome others of their Progeny.</p>
               <p>4. <hi>Filius Eccleſiae in patribus Verſatiſsimus:</hi> This ſon of the Church of <hi>England</hi> was moſt familiar with the antient Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers both of the Eaſt &amp; Weſt. Of the Greek, <hi>Chryſoſtom</hi> lay in his boſome, even till he did <hi>patrizare,</hi> become like unto him in his flowing ſtyle and golden eloquence. Among the Latine, St. <hi>Augustine,</hi> that maul of hereticks, was in chief eſteem with him.</p>
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:51903:92"/>
               <p>5. He was an exact Hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rian, for Eccleſiaſticals eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, thoſe Records of the Church: the ignorance where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of is the mother of many of our growing errours and indevoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Nor was he leſſe acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Schooles; (though more delighted with the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of <hi>Siloah</hi> then of <hi>Meriba;</hi>) even a Maſter of the Maſter of the Sentences, and <hi>à Secretiori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus</hi> unto the Councils, even of their Cabinet.</p>
               <p>6. And becauſe the flock is not onely to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed but cured ſometime; he was a ſingular Caſuiſt, and ſpiritual Chyrur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, that knew well <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, to ſet in joint again, and to bind up the broken heart: a Soul-Chyrurgion right, for all thoſe
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:51903:93"/> properties of heart, and hand, and eye: no leſſe ſweet and ſoft in his exhortations &amp; conſola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, then ſharp and impartial in his reproofs and reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions. He was indeed another <hi>Apollos,</hi> an eloquent man and mighty in the Scriptures: And as a nother <hi>Baſil,</hi> he did thun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der in in his doctrine, and ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in his life. His light ſhined before men; not onely that of knowledge, but that of exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple alſo, in his Piety and Chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, in his gravity and ſweet a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility.</p>
               <p>7. He was at laſt dignified with the Arch deaconry of <hi>Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheſter;</hi> and having been above three and thirty years Rector of S. <hi>Mary Woolnoth</hi> in <hi>Lum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bard-ſtreet, London;</hi> an indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable,
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:51903:93"/> moſt faithful and moſt beloved preacher of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel there; Lamenting the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtractions, fallen upon the Church, he departed hence to reſt with God, <hi>Iu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</hi> 23. 1643.</p>
               <byline>Out of Mr. Edward Sparke's Preface to <hi>Sarah</hi> and <hi>Hagar.</hi>
               </byline>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="biography">
               <head>VIII. FRANCIS BACON Lord <hi>Verulam.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>FRancis Bacon</hi> the Adorner and Ornament of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, was born in <hi>Yorkſhire Ian.</hi> 22. 1560. His father was Sir <hi>Nicholas Bacon,</hi> Lord Keeper, that prudent Counſellour to <hi>Queen Elizabeth:</hi> His Mother the Daughter of Sir <hi>Anthony
<pb n="176" facs="tcp:51903:94"/> Cook,</hi> a Lady eminent for Piety and Learning. Theſe being the Parents, you may eaſily ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſue was like to be.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He was ſo pregnant in his Childhood, that the <hi>Queen</hi> took notice of him and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted much, then, to confer with him, and to prove him with Queſtions; unto whom he delivered himſelf with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turity above his years, that her Majeſtie would often term him, <hi>The young Lord Keeper.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. Whileſt he was commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> in <hi>Trinity</hi> Colledge, under the Tuition of Dr. <hi>Whitgift</hi> (afterward the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned Arch-B. of <hi>Cant.</hi>) being about ſixteen years of age, he firſt fell into the diſlike of <hi>Ariſtotles</hi> Philoſophy (yet ſtill
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:51903:94"/> attributing high Attributes to the Authour) as a Phyloſopher onely ſtrong for diſputations and contentions, but barren of the production of works for the benefit of the life of man. In which mind he continued to his dying day.</p>
               <p n="4">4. After he had paſſed the circle of the liberal Arts, his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thought fit to frame and mould him for the Arts of State, and for that end ſent him over into <hi>France</hi> with the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadour. In his abſence, his Father dying, left him being the youngeſt Son, in ſome ſtreights: till after ſome years he ſucceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the eſtate of his deareſt brother Sir <hi>Anthony Bacon,</hi> a Gentleman equall to him in height of wit, though inferiour in learning.</p>
               <p n="5">
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:51903:95"/>5. Being returned from tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vel, he applyed himſelf to the ſtudy of the Canon Law, which he took upon him to be his profeſſion, and ſeated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for the Commodity of his Studies and Practice in <hi>Greys Inne,</hi> where he erected that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legant pile or ſtructure, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly known by the name of <hi>The Lord Bacons Lodgings.</hi> In which houſe he carried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with that Comity and Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity, that he was much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced and loved by the Readers and Gentlemen of the Houſe.</p>
               <p n="6">6. His Birth and Capacities qualified him, above others of his profeſſion to have ordinary Acceſſes at Court, and to come frequently into the <hi>Queens</hi> eye,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:51903:95"/> who received from him great ſatisfaction not onely in buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Law, but alſo about Affairs of State. Yet was he kept back from preferment in the <hi>Queens</hi> time by the policie of a great States-man, then: leſt, if he had riſen, he might have obſcured his Glory. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhe gave him a dry Rever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Regiſters Office in <hi>Star-Chamber</hi> (which fell not till after her Majeſties time) of which he uſed to ſay: <hi>That it was like another mans ground, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>tting upon his houſe; which might mend his proſpect, but it did not fill his Barn.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. After the coming in of his new Maſter <hi>King Iames,</hi> he made a great progreſſe: Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citour, Atturney, Counſellour,
<pb n="180" facs="tcp:51903:96"/> Keeper, and laſtly Chancellour: (which two laſt places, though they be the ſame in Authority and power; yet they differ in Patent,) ſince whoſe time, none of his Succeſſours did e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver bear the Title of <hi>Lord Chancellour.</hi> 
                  <note n="*" place="margin">
                     <hi>But ſince the writing hereof, the Nation is happy in the right Honourable</hi> Edward <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> Hide <hi>L. high</hi> Chancellour <hi>of</hi> England.</note>
               </p>
               <p n="8">8. Towards his riſing years, not before, he entered into a married eſtate, and took to wife one of the daughters and co heirs of Alderman <hi>Barnhim.</hi> Children he had none, yet he had other Iſſues to perpetuate his name; the Iſſues of his Brain; in which he was ever happy and admired. Neither did the want of children detract from the good uſage of his Conſort, whom he proſecuted
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:51903:96"/> with much conjugal Love and Reſpect.</p>
               <p n="9">9. The laſt five years of his life, being withdrawn from Civil affairs and from an active life, he employed wholly in Contemplation and ſtudies, a thing whereof his Lordſhip would often ſpeak, during his Active life: as if he affected to die in the Shade, and not in the Light. In which time, he compoſed the greateſt part of his Books and Writings, both in Engliſh and Latine. Some of them are theſe: <hi>King Henry the Seventh. Natural Hiſtory. The Advancement of Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. Eſſayes. Miſcellanies,</hi> and the chiefeſt in his account, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauratio magna &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. Thoſe Abilities which commonly go ſingle in other
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:51903:97"/> men were all conjoyned, &amp; met in him. Theſe are, ſharpneſſe of Wit, Memory, Judgement, and Elocution. Sir <hi>Walter Ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leigh</hi> ſaid of him by way of Compariſon: <hi>That the Earl of Salisbury was an excellent Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker, but no good Pen-man; That the Earl of Northampton was an excellent Pen-man, but no good ſpeaker; But that Sir Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis Bacon was eminent in both.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">11. In the compoſing of his Books, he did rather drive at a maſculine and a clear Expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then at any ſineneſſe or affectation of phraſes; and would often ask, if the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing were expreſſed plain e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, as being one that ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted words to be but ſubſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vient or miniſterial to matter,
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:51903:97"/> and not the principal. And if his ſtile were polite, it was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he could do no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe.</p>
               <p n="12">12. His meals were refecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the ear, as well as of the ſtomack: wherein a man might be refreſhed in his mind and underſtanding, no leſſe then in his body. In which Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations he would not appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priate the Speech wholly to himſelf, but draw out others and allure them to take their turns, and ſpeak upon ſuch a ſubject as he knew they were skilfull in. Neither contemned he any mans Obſervations, but would light his torch at every mans candle.</p>
               <p n="13">13. When his office called him to charge any offenders,
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:51903:98"/> though it was his duty to charge them home, yet he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver inſulted over them, but was alwayes tender hearted, and carried, himſelf decently to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the parties; as one, that looked upon the example with the eye of ſeverity, but upon the perſon with the eye of pity and compaſſion. And in Civil Buſineſſe, as he was Councel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of Eſtate, he had the beſt way of adviſing, not engage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Maſter in any precipitate or grievous Courſes; and the King gave him this teſtimony, that he ever dealt <hi>ſuavibus mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dis,</hi> in a moderate and fair way.</p>
               <p n="14">14. He was a good Maſter to his Servants, and rewarded their long attendance with good places freely, when they
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:51903:98"/> fell into his power. Which was the cauſe that ſo many young Gentlemen of bloud and quality ſought to liſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in his retinue. And if he were abuſed by any of them in their places, it was onely the errour of the goodneſſe of his Nature, but the badge of their indiſcretions and intemperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces.</p>
               <p n="15">15. This Lord was religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous: for though the world be apt to ſuſpect and prejudge great wits and politicks to have ſomewhat of the Atheiſt; yet he was converſant with God, as appeareth by ſeveral paſſages throughout the whole Current of his writings. Otherwiſe, he ſhould have croſſed his own principle, <hi>That a little Phyloſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy
<pb n="186" facs="tcp:51903:99"/> maketh man apt to forget God, as attributing too much to ſecond Cauſes; but depth of Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophy brings a man back to God again.</hi> He repaired frequently, to the ſervice of the Church, to Sermons, to the Sacrament, &amp; dyed in the true Faith eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="16">16. He was free from Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, which (as he ſaid himſelf) <hi>He never bred, nor fed.</hi> He was no revenger of injuries: no heaver of men out of their pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as delighting in their ruine; no defamer of any man to his Prince. His Fame is greater and ſounds louder in forreign parts abroad, then at home in his own Nation. Several per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of quality croſſed the ſeas on purpoſe to gain an opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:51903:99"/> of ſeeing him and diſcourſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with him. He dyed at <hi>High gate Apr.</hi> 9. An. 1626. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>at.</hi> 66. of a gentle Feaver, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied accidentally with a great Cold, and was buried at <hi>S. Albans.</hi>
               </p>
               <byline>Out of his Life written by <hi>Dr. Rawley.</hi>
               </byline>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="biography">
               <head>IX. THOMAS JACKSON, D. D.</head>
               <p n="1">1. HE was firſt planted in <hi>Queens</hi> Colledge un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Tuition of Dr. <hi>Cracan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorp,</hi> and from thence remo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved to <hi>Corpus-Chriſti.</hi> Though he had no notice of the vacan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the place till the day be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Election, yet he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered with ſo much readineſs
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:51903:100"/> and applauſe, that he gained the admiration as well as the Suffrages of the Electours, and was choſen with full conſent, although they had received let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of favour from great men for another Scholar; the <hi>Mandamus</hi> of the pious Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, <hi>Nec prece nec pretio,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailing more then all other ſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitations.</p>
               <p n="2">2. He preſerved the high opinion which was conceived of him, by a ſtudious and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary life, not ſubject to the u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſual intemperances of that age. Certainly the devil could not finde him idle, nor at leiſure to have the ſuggeſtions of vice whiſpered in his ear. And al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though many in their youthful times have their deviations and
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:51903:100"/> exorbitancies, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards prove reformed and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent men; yet it pleaſed God to keep him in a conſtant path of piety and virtue.</p>
               <p n="3">3. He was furniſhed with all the learned Languages, Arts and Sciences, as the praevious diſpoſitions or beautiful Gate, which led him to the Temple; but eſpecially Metaphyſicks, as the next in attendance, and moſt neceſſary handmaid to <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity;</hi> which was the miſtreſs, where all his thoughts were fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed, being wholly taken up with the love and admiration of Jeſus Chriſt, and him cruci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied. The Reading to young<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Scholars, and ſome employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments impoſed by the Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, were rather Recreations
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:51903:101"/> and Aſſiſtances, then divertiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments from that intended work. The Offices he under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took (out of duty, not deſire) were never the moſt profitable<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but the more ingenious; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſuch as might fill his purſe, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> encreaſe his knowledge. When he was choſen into Office, the Governour of the Colledge was wont to give this teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of him, <hi>That he was a man moſt ſincere in Elections,</hi> and that in a dubious Victory o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> younger wits, it was the ſafeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> experiment for an happy choice, to ſollow the <hi>omen</hi> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> his judgement.</p>
               <p n="4">4. He read a Lecture of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity in the Colledge every Sunday morning, and another day of the week at <hi>Pembrok<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
                  <pb n="191" facs="tcp:51903:101"/> Colledge (then newly erected) by the inſtance of the Maſters and Fellowes there. He was choſen Vice-Preſident for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny years together, who by his place was to moderate the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſputations in Divinity. In all theſe he demeaned himſelf with great depth of learning, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied with all gentleneſs, curteſy, humility and modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p n="5">5. From the Colledge he was preferred to a Living in the Biſhoprick of <hi>Durham</hi> (in their donation) and from thence re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved to the Vicarage of <hi>New-Caſtle.</hi> This was the place where he was firſt appointed by his friends to be a Merchant; but he choſe rather to be a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor for heaven. Here he a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorned
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:51903:102"/> the Goſpel which he preached, with an humble and charitable Converſation; gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving uſually to the poor, when he went abroad, what money he had, who at length flocked ſo unto him, that his ſervant took care he ſhould not have too much in his pocket. After ſome years, he was invited back again to the Colledge, being choſen <hi>Preſident</hi> in his abſence, at ſo great a diſtance, ſo unex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectedly without any ſuit or petition upon his part, that he knew nothing of the vacancy of the place, but by the ſame let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters that informed him, it was conferred upon himſelf.</p>
               <p n="6">6. Upon his return to <hi>Ox<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford,</hi> and admiſſion to his Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, they found no alte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:51903:102"/> by his long abſence, and more converſe with the world, but that he appeared yet more humble in his elder times; and this not out of coldneſſe and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of Spirit, but from a prudent choice &amp; experience of a better way. He ruled in a moſt obliging ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, no man depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from him with a ſad heart, except they had by ſome willing errour created trouble to him. The Friends as well as the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory of his Predeceſſors, he uſed fairly. A lover and maker of peace, ſilencing and compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing all differences, diſpleaſures and animoſities by a prudent impartiality, and the example of his own ſweet diſpoſition. It was a new and peculiar Art of Diſcipline, but ſucceſſeful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:51903:103"/> practiſed by him, that thoſe under his Authourity were kept within bounds and order, not ſo much out of fear of the penalty, as out of love of the Governour. He took notice of that which was good in the worſt men, and made that an occaſion to commend them for the goods ſake; and living himſelf very ſtrictly, yet reſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved large Pardons for imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections of others.</p>
               <p n="7">7. He willingly admitted, and was much delighted in the acquaintance and familiarity of hopeful young Divines, not deſpiſing their Youth, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counting them as Sons and Brethren, encouraging and ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſing them what Books to read, and with what holy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parations,
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:51903:103"/> lending them ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch Books as they had need of. This was one of the ſpecial ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and directions which he commended to young men: <hi>Quod dubit as nefeceris;</hi> Heare the dictates of your own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience. He was as diffuſive of his knowledge, counſel and advice, as of any other his works of mercy.</p>
               <p n="8">8. In all Hiſtories of learned, pious and devout men, you ſhall ſcarcely meet with one that diſdained the world more generouſly: not out of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of it, as one brought up in Cells and darkneſſe, for he was known and endeared to men of the moſt reſplendent fortunes; nor out of melan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>choly diſpoſition, for he was
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:51903:104"/> he was chearful and content in all eſtates; but out of a due and deliberate ſcorn, knowing the true value, that is, the vanity of it. As preferments were heaped upon him without his ſuit, or knowledge, ſo there was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in his power to give, which he was not ready and willing to part withall, to the deſerving or indigent man. He knew, it was a more bleſſed thing to give then to receive; in all places of his abode, diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buting to the poor with a free heart, a bountiful hand, a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable ſpeech, and a chearful eye. How diſreſpectful was he of Mammon, the god of this world, the golden image which Kings and Potentates have ſet up: before whom the
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:51903:104"/> Trumpets play for war and ſlaugh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er, and Nations and Languages fall down and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, beſides all other kind of Muſick for jollity and delight, to drown (if it were poſſible) the noiſe of bloud, which is moſt audible and cryes loudeſt in the ears of the Almighty. How eaſily could he caſt that a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, for which others throw away their lives and ſalvation, running headlong into the place of eternal skreekings, weeping and gnaſhing of teeth. If it were not for this ſpirit of Cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſneſſe, all the world would be at quiet. Certainly (although the nature of man be an apt ſoil for ſin to flouriſh in, yet) if the love of money be the root of all evill, it could not
<pb n="198" facs="tcp:51903:105"/> grow up in him, becauſe it had no root: and if it be ſo hard for a rich man to enter into the Kingdome of God and the narrow way which leads unto life, then he that ſtooped ſo low by humbleneſſe of minde, and emptied himſelf ſo neerly by mercifulneſſe to the poor, muſt needs find an eaſier paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage. Doubtleſſe, they that ſay and do theſe things, ſhew plainly that they ſeek another Countrey, that is, an Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly: for if they had been mindful of This, they might have taken opportunity to have uſed it more advantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly.</p>
               <p n="9">9. His Devotions towards God were aſſiduous and exem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plary, both in publick and
<pb n="199" facs="tcp:51903:105"/> private. When he went the yearly progreſſe to view the Colledge Lands, and came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Tenants Houſe, it was his conſtant cuſtome (before any other buſineſſe, diſcourſe or care of himſelf, were he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo wet or weary) to call for a retiring room to pour out his Soul unto God, who led him ſafely in his Journey. And this he did not out of any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious pretence of Holineſſe, to devour a Widows houſe with more Facility, rack their Rents, or enhance their Fines; for excepting the conſtant Reuenue to the Founder (to whom he was a ſtrict accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant) no man ever did more for them, or leſſe for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.</p>
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:51903:106"/>
               <p>1. As he was alwayes a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciler of Differences in his private Government, ſo he ſeriouſly lamented the publick breaches of the Kingdome. He well knew that war was commonly attended with ruin and calamity, eſpecially to Church and Church-men. But God took him from the evils to come. It was a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient degree of puniſhment to him to foreſee it: it had been more then a thouſand deaths unto him, to have beheld it with his eyes. When his death was approaching, he was ever heard repeating to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with a ſoft voice theſe and the like ejaculations: <hi>I wait for the Lord</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Gratious is the Lord</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Return unto thy
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:51903:106"/> rest, O my Soul, &amp;c.</hi> And hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thus ſpoken, ſoon after he rendered up his Spirit to Him that gave it.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="biography">
               <head>X. The LADY FALKLAND.</head>
               <p n="1">1. <hi>THis elect Lady ſet out early in the wayes of God, in the dawn of her age. She came not from her Nurſes armes without ſome knowledge of the Principles of Chriſtian Religion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. <hi>Her obedience to her Parents was ſo exact, that her Mother would ſay, She remembred not any one particular, wherein at any time, ſhe diſobe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ed her ſelf or her Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>When ſhe was very young, ſhe wrought a purſe for her own Almes and would importunately begge her Mothers ſingle money to fill it, that ſhe might empty it again to the poor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="4">
                  <pb n="202" facs="tcp:51903:107"/>4. <hi>She was oſt tims at a book in her cloſet, when ſhe was thought to be a bed. Hours of private prayer ſhe conſtantly obſerved, and if ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers were in her own room, ſhe would retire into ſome other for that purpoſe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="5">5. <hi>After her Marriage, though ſhe acknowledged Gods great good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to her for her temporal prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, yet was not her heart any whit perceiv'd to be exalted with joy for them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the death of her Lord, ſhe addreſſes her ſelf to a Divine of great eminency for piety and learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and from him ſhe takes dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction for a more ſtrict courſe of life in this her widdowhood.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="7">7. <hi>Her grand employment was to underſtand and practice our Saviours Sermon in the Mount, and ſhe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan with thoſe virtues, to which the beatitudes are annexed, Humility, Meekneſſe &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="8">
                  <pb n="203" facs="tcp:51903:107"/>8. <hi>She excelled in mercifulneſſe, Some of her neighbours that were very old, and not able to work, or very young, and not fit to work, were wholly maintained by her. To other poor Children ſhe contributed much, both for their ſpiritual and temporal well-being, by erecting a School for them, where they were to be taught both to read and to work. And ſhe accounted that the beſt contrivement of her eſtate, which ſet moſt poor people to work.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="9">9. <hi>When it was objected that idle beggers were relieved at her doors, ſhe ſaid, I had rather relieve five unworthy vagrants, then that one member of Chriſt ſhould go empty away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="10">10. <hi>She was wont to ſend plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful relief privately to priſons and needy perſons, with a ſtrict charge, that it ſhould not be known from whence it came. And ſhe failed not to relieve her enemies as oft as occaſion required.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="11">
                  <pb n="204" facs="tcp:51903:108"/>11. <hi>She uſed to provide Cordials for the ſick and to viſit them her ſelf (even the pooreſt) and carry with her ſome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ook of ſpiritual exhortation and read to them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="12">12. <hi>The morning and evening prayers of the Church were conſtant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly uſed in her family, and her ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants charged to be preſent. And on the Lords day ſhe roſe earlier then ordinary, and enjoyned her ſelf much private duty beſides the publick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="13">13. <hi>She had two Cautions for her Tongue: Never to ſpeak evill of any, but onely to reclaim him: and that her words ſhould not be idle but tend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to edification.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="14">14. <hi>She agreed with her fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar friends, to take the liberty of reproving one another, ſaying,</hi> There is no true friendſhip without this. <hi>If you ſuffer me to be undone for ever, how are we friends?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:51903:108"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
